<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ruin to ruin, after misery to misery being the distressed, and ruined, and perishing state of the loyal and faithful seamen of England, and wherein is laid down : I. their ruined state in several particulars, II. that it is like to be three or four years more before they are paid, except an extraordinary supply be raised, and appropriated for them, III. that as many ships, and thousands and ten thousands of men have five or six years pay due, if they are not timely paid, it is like to be eight or nine years between their beginning to earn their money and their being paid, IV. a proposal humbly offered how they may be paid off, all by May next, without borrowing one penny of money, V. several reasons for their being justly and honestly paid, VI. an humble proposal for the advantage of a million or two in a year to the nation in a few years, and lastly, an humble supplication for the taking off some part of the act of Parliament concerning the poor miserable seamens paying 6d the month out of their wages / all humbly represented by ... William Hodges.</title>
            <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12515210</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12515210</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62670</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62670)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 670:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ruin to ruin, after misery to misery being the distressed, and ruined, and perishing state of the loyal and faithful seamen of England, and wherein is laid down : I. their ruined state in several particulars, II. that it is like to be three or four years more before they are paid, except an extraordinary supply be raised, and appropriated for them, III. that as many ships, and thousands and ten thousands of men have five or six years pay due, if they are not timely paid, it is like to be eight or nine years between their beginning to earn their money and their being paid, IV. a proposal humbly offered how they may be paid off, all by May next, without borrowing one penny of money, V. several reasons for their being justly and honestly paid, VI. an humble proposal for the advantage of a million or two in a year to the nation in a few years, and lastly, an humble supplication for the taking off some part of the act of Parliament concerning the poor miserable seamens paying 6d the month out of their wages / all humbly represented by ... William Hodges.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, William, Sir, 1645?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed five or six hundred of these humbly to give away to the most Honourable Houses of Parliament, but none to sell about streets,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 43.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sailors --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62670:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62670:1"/>
            <p>RUIN to RUIN, AFTER MISERY to MISERY.</p>
            <p>Being the diſtreſſed, and Ruined, and periſhing State of the Loyal and Faithful Seamen of <hi>England,</hi> and wherein is laid down.</p>
            <p n="1">I. their ruined State in ſeveral particulars.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That it is like to be three or four Years more before they are paid, except an extraordinary Supply be raiſed, and appropriated for them.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That as many Ships, and thouſands and ten thouſands of Men have five or ſix years pay due, if they are not timely paid, it is like to be eight or nine Years between their beginning to earn their Money, and their being paid.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. A Propoſal humbly offered how they may be paid off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by <hi>May</hi> next, without borrowing one penny of Money.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Several Reaſons for their being Juſtly and Honeſtly paid.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. An humble Propoſal for the advantage of a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion or two in a Year to the Nation in a few Years, And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> An humble Supplication for the taking off ſome part of the Act of Parliament concerning the poor miſerable Seamens paying 6d. the Month out of their Wages.</p>
            <p>All humbly repreſented by a faithful Subject to his Majeſty, and Servant to the Parliament and Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Hodges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, five or ſix hundred of theſe humbly to give away to the moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament, but none to ſell about Streets. 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62670:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62670:2"/>
            <head>TO The moſt Excellent Majeſty of King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Third, and to the Two moſt Honourable Houſes, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled, humbly Sheweth.</head>
            <head type="sub">May it pleaſe your Moſt Gracious Majeſty, and you the moſt Noble, Right Noble and Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Senators.</head>
            <p>THE Providence of God having ſtirred me up for ſome years laſt paſt, to repreſent the dreadful Ruin and Miſery and Deſtruction of the Loyal and Valiant Seamen of <hi>England,</hi> in the Deſtruction of their Lives, Health, and payment, in ſuch a moſt deplorable Caſe as is in no Age or Hiſtory Record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that I could hear or read of either of theſe Nations, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, for the Sea-faring part of Mankind. And there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been an Act of Parliament or two concerning their Relief, it may be ſuppoſed now all is well. But what ſhall I ſay, their Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have been in ſome caſes worſe than before; as firſt, before thoſe Acts, there were many Ships had three or four years Pay due to them, and now there is many have five or ſix Years Pay due to them. Secondly, Before they had, it may be, ten hundred thouſand Pound due to them, but they have had above eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred thouſand Pound due to them for Wages, as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Commons in their votes laſt <hi>March</hi> declared was due to them at <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> 1697. And though there was a Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62670:3"/>laſt Winter of near forty Ships, there were not four of them paid clearly off, but want to be Re call'd many thouſands of Payments, and of above two hundred Ships put up for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 97, there is above an hundred of them not paid one Groat ſince, and ſo there is ſome thouſands of Payments of above 4, 5, and 6 years ſtanding, as by the Printed Liſt put up at the <hi>Navy-Office,</hi> and of the Ships names and times of Payment, will appear, two of which Liſt I intend to preſent to the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Speakers of the <hi>Houſes of Lords and Commons,</hi> for the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to peruſe, and two to preſent to his Grace the <hi>Archbiſhop of Canterbury,</hi> one for himſelf, and the other for his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and there every one may ſee that thoſe poor Wretches Families that had run the hazard of <hi>Starving and periſhing,</hi> by lying out of their <hi>honeſt Pay</hi> 3 or 4 Years, have now, to add to their full Ruin and Deſtruction, <hi>if poſſible,</hi> lain out 5 or 6 years or more, and there is <hi>ten or eleven</hi> Ships now at this time at <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> that have not been paid off this 4 or 5 years, moſt part, and having between <hi>Three and four hundred Thouſand Pound</hi> due to them, as by the ſeveral Ships Books will appear; and though their Miſeries have been ſo great, yet the Nation has been put to ſome <hi>hundreds of thouſands of Pounds</hi> of <hi>needleſs Charge,</hi> that might have been ſaved, if they had been paid off when the War was ended, and as I ſaid, there are many other Ships of <hi>ſeveral Years ſtanding</hi> unpaid, that counting there was laſt year 1800000 pound due for Sea-Wages, and ſuppoſe 600000 paid ſince, <hi>four hundred Thouſand</hi> grown due ſince, it will be found to be about <hi>Sixteen hundred Thouſand Pound</hi> due at this Day for Wages; and how dreadfully <hi>ruined and Starving</hi> a Condition thoſe Families muſt be in who have not had one Penny to ſupport them with Bread or Cloaths <hi>to keep them from ſtarving</hi> for 5 <hi>or</hi> 6 <hi>Years,</hi> cannot eaſily be known, nor eaſily Lamented, and as they have been <hi>worſe paid,</hi> ſo alſo have they been worſe fed ſince the <hi>Act of Parliament for their Relief;</hi> for before this <hi>Act</hi> ſometimes a Ship was put to ſhort Allowance for a few Weeks at Sea in Caſe of Neceſſity. But after the <hi>Act for their Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement,</hi> they were moſt part of the <hi>Summer,</hi> and the greateſt part of the Fleet put to <hi>Short Allowauce, Six M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to have but four Mens Victuals,</hi> and that a great part of the Year 1697; and not only at <hi>Sea,</hi> but in <hi>Harbours</hi> at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and at <hi>Chatham,</hi> and wanted Bread at the <hi>Buoy of the Nore,</hi> as the Books of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62670:3"/>whole Fleet will make appear, and therefore let their incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have appeared to be what it will, their diſcouragement was Augmented; and for that, and for ſome other <hi>Reaſons.</hi> I would humbly entreat for the <hi>Loyal Seamen of England,</hi> that ſome part of that Act may be Repealed, or altered. But the firſt thing, which I believe both God and Juſtice, and <hi>Moral Honeſty,</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> requires, is, to pay the <hi>Labourers,</hi> theſe miſerable, poor, impoveriſhed, beggered, ruined and undone Wretches, their Wages due to them, for their hire, that after the laying down of above <hi>Sixty Thouſand</hi> of their Lives, and the Ruin and Running of above <hi>an Hundred Thouſand</hi> of their Payments, that they are ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of by thoſe fatal Letters, <hi>Q. R.</hi> The reſt of their Payments not Raviſhed from them as yet openly, being near <hi>an Hundred and Forty Thouſand</hi> Payments; may be honeſtly and ſpeedily paid them; and that the <hi>Nation</hi> need not to excuſe the Paying of them for want of Money, I would humbly propoſe how there might be the full <hi>Payment</hi> of them with Eaſe, before <hi>Lady-day,</hi> without Borrowing a Groat: That is, by the Iſſuing out of <hi>ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen,</hi> or 18 <hi>hundred Thouſand Pounds of Chequer-Bills,</hi> as before; but they muſt be appropriated for the <hi>Payment of the Fleet only;</hi> for if there be five times as much raiſed, and it runs in other Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, the Seamen may be as <hi>Miſerable,</hi> and as <hi>Ruined</hi> ſtill as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. I bleſs God, Since I did write great part of this, that God hath put it into the Hearts of the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> to enquire into the ſtate of the <hi>Sea Affairs,</hi> to ſee what is due, and what hath been paid ſince there was <hi>Eighteen hundred, and ſixty Thouſand Pound due at Michaelmas</hi> 1697, for Wages to the Fleet. But I would humbly intreat their Honours to Conſider, <hi>That the Number of the Seamen in our Fleet, and Ships in our Fleet was much more than ever before, and perhaps a quarter more than need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> if they had been led on to fight, by their Managers, as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ages. And it may be ſome will ſuppoſe, becauſe there was about 37 Ships paid off the very Laſt Winter, altho' the Recalls was never paid, which perhaps is twice or three times as much, and becauſe there hath been, it may be, twenty or thirty Ships Paid this year, though by the way, many of them have above a Year and quarters pay due ſtill of the New, and ſome of them ſeveral Years of the Old. But it may be ſome will ſuppoſe the Fleet paid off, when as there were about 160 Ships Employed, as your Honours will ſind; and if <hi>Forty Ships</hi> Paid in a Year, will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62670:4"/>be four Years in Paying at that Rate, and yet make a great noiſe, to pay off <hi>ten Ships</hi> every 12 or 13 Weeks, and at that rate of paying off <hi>Thirty or Forty Ships</hi> in the Year, muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be two or three years made in payment of them off, and then for the <hi>Recalls</hi> of the Hundred and odd <hi>Ships</hi> un-recalled, as by the printed Liſt will appear, if they begin to recall them, and pay off a Ship every Week, it muſt be above two Years time in Paying them, and the Ships that were pretended to be Paid off laſt Year, and having ſo many Thouſands now left unpaid; if they be Paid off fully, one Ship in a Week, will be near ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Years Work. So that, unleſs God Almighty put it into your Honours Hearts for to conſider their Ruined Caſe, here is like to be of Neceſſity three or four Years time more, before the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined, Begger'd Seamen be all paid, as any that will but count the Number of the Ships aforeſaid, may eaſily find; or if your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours would but count the more than <hi>two Millions of Wages due for Pay of the Fleet ſince the 1ſt of</hi> October 1697. and what is Paid ſince, and if your Honours find that there hath not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Seven or Eight Hundred Thouſand Pound paid in the Year</hi> 1697. <hi>and</hi> 1698. Then at that rate, conſidering the great Number of Ships pretended to be paid, that have above a Year and a quarters Pay already, and the growing Pay coming due, it will require 3 or 4 Years time to Pay them off at that rate, which will be <hi>Miſery to Miſery,</hi> and <hi>Ruin to Ruin:</hi> And if it ſhould be objected, that the Army muſt be Paid off firſt; to that I would humbly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That if the Honourable Houſes will raiſe <hi>Three millions of Exchequer-Bills,</hi> it would pay off the <hi>Fleet,</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> before <hi>May-Day,</hi> and ſave his Majeſty the Trouble and Charge of Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Money at I know not what prodigious Charge, Procuration, and Continuation; and theſe Three Millions of Bills would be of uſe to his Majeſty, and the Nation, and either ſave the hoarding up of our <hi>Ready-money</hi> by the Great, and Rich; or theſe Bills, if returned but twenty times in a Year, or thirty times in two Years, one Bill with another, among Tradeſmen, they might, at ten in the <hi>Hundred</hi> Profit, gain the Value of the Bills three times over; and we find by daily experience now, that thoſe <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Bills</hi> now out, are hoarded up, and eſteemed better than Gold or Silver; and as to calling in of the 3 Millions of Bills, the Honourable Houſe of Commons might ſettle a ſufficient Fund, either by a 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> aid, as this laſt Year, or by what means and ways
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62670:4"/>their Honours in their great Wiſdoms do think ſit. But that there is a neceſſity of paying off the miſerable, Ragged, Ruined Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and their Beggered, and Periſhing Widows, Wives, or Relations: I have humbly preſumed to lay down ſeveral Reaſons, and if any ſhould ask why I do put my ſelf to the Charge and Hazard to repreſent their Ruin, having not bought one Penny of their Pay theſe 4 or 5 Years, to that I would humbly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That their Ruin, and Deſtruction, and ſtarving Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them and their Family cries ſo loud in my Ears, and afflicts my very Soul, that I cannot forbear Repreſenting their miſerable Caſel, having known ſo much of their Continued Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery ſo many Years, that I have a Call from God, Angels, and Men, and my own Conſcience, not to let their Ruins be hid; and if God Almighty Commanded the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law not to let their <hi>enemies Ox or Aſs lye in a Ditch without helping him out;</hi> Then certainly God will be well pleaſed that I ſhould Labour to help His Majeſty, and the Nations loving and faithful, ſerviceable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Seamen and their Families, that lye in the Ditches of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and Ruin, to help them out, by endeavouring to cry out to His Majeſty, and your Honours.</p>
            <p>I Remember a Story I have read in the <hi>Book of Martyrs,</hi> that it was a Saying of an Outlandiſh Prieſt in the times of Popery, That <hi>the Engliſhmen were good Aſſes, and would bear all Burthens.</hi> And I do believe I may ſay in the Preſence of the Lord, before whom I write, That there were never ſuch a number of faithful, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, contented Aſſes belong'd to the Sea in any Ages of the World, who died and periſhed at that dreadful Rate, above 60 Thouſand of them, as the Ships Books prove, and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a hundred Thouſand of them run out of their Pay, and the reſt kept ſo many Years out of their Pay, and be contented to dye and periſh without Speaking a Word of it; and I muſt ſay, <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Aſs was wiſe enough to tell his Caſe, and for my part, they are like never to know from me that they are any other Creatures. But Aſſes bear Aſſes Burthens, and if I were their Mouth, I would ſay, to the Nations in the words of <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Aſs; <hi>Are we not your Aſſes, upon which ye have Riden over ſince we were yours, and did we ever Rebel againſt you, and wherefore have you ſmitten us theſe three times ſo dreadfully out of our Lines, Liberties, and Payments.</hi> And I ſuppoſe ſome will not Repreſent their Caſe, becauſe they cannot,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62670:5"/>and ſome others that know their Ruins, get Eſtates by it, in buying many of their Tickets at eight, or ten, or twelve <hi>Shillings</hi> in the <hi>Pound</hi> Loſs, which is the Devil and all of <hi>Extortion,</hi> and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>will Cry in the Ears of God, Angels, and Men,</hi> either for the Relief of the Oppreſſed, and puniſhing the dreadful <hi>Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners,</hi> or <hi>Vengeance</hi> on the <hi>Oppreſſors;</hi> and indeed, I have read much in the <hi>Prophets,</hi> of the <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> and <hi>Extortioners,</hi> that God complain'd of againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but could never find, neither in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor in <hi>Joſephus</hi>'s Hiſtory, or any other Hiſtory, that there was any could parallel the Extortion, and Ruin exerciſed on the brave, Couragious Seamen of <hi>England.</hi> I ſhall ſay more in the Reaſons following, and leave all to the Serious Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of His Gratious Majeſty, and the two moſt Honourable Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and lay my ſelf at their Feet, humbly begging Fardon for whatever is amiſs in this, or me; and either in doing, or Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, ſhall ſtill ſubſcribe my ſelf to be His Majeſty's Moſt Humble, and Hearty, and Loving Servant to Command,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hermitage-Bridge,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 1699.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>William Hodges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62670:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ruin to Ruin,</hi> AFTER MISERY to MISERY.</head>
            <head type="sub">Or the afflicted, diſtreſſed, impoveriſhed, and Ruined State of many Thouſands and ten Thouſands of the poor and miſerable Seamen, their periſhing Wives, Widows, Children, or Relations, Sheweth,</head>
            <p>THat as the <hi>Greatneſs of the Loyal and faithful Seamens Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries</hi> were thrown on them after they had beaten the <hi>French,</hi> ſo the <hi>Providence of God</hi> called me to repreſent the ſame from Year to Year, in part, to the two moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Houſes of Parliament;</hi> and their <hi>Honours</hi> having raiſed Money for them for their Relief; and made two Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, entituled, <hi>For their Relief.</hi> I was in hopes I ſhould have had no more occaſion to repreſent their being ruined; but their Caſe being ſo exceeding miſerable ſtill, as to their Pay, I cannot as a <hi>Chriſtian, or an Engliſhman,</hi> with Love to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and my <hi>Native Country,</hi> and ſatisfaction of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> let their <hi>Diſtreſs</hi> be any longer hidden; eſpecially conſidering that as the <hi>Honourable Houſes</hi> raiſed great Sums, and entitled an Act or two, as if it had been to pay them off; it may be ſome will ſuppoſe that the <hi>Seamen</hi> are Paid, and there being many <hi>Honourable new Members of Parliament,</hi> which it may be never heard of the <hi>Dreadful Ruin of thoſe poor Wretches,</hi> I do humbly preſume to repreſent the ſame in all Humility, Truth, and Faithfullneſs, and if any will ſay they are moſt part paid, it is againſt the proof of all the Ships Books at the Pay-Office at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 1697. And if we reckon but 340 <hi>Thouſand pound</hi> more for the reſt of the Year, and I will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62670:6"/>prove by the ſeveral <hi>Ships</hi> Books that there are ſeveral <hi>Ships</hi> have not been paid off this 4 or 5 <hi>Years,</hi> and I will prove by a <hi>Liſt</hi> of about <hi>two hundred Ships</hi> put up for <hi>Recalls</hi> at <hi>Broadſtreet</hi> in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1697. That there is above an <hi>Hundred</hi> of them not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called;</hi> and the <hi>Liſt</hi> ſhews how many <hi>Years thoſe miſerable Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are unpaid;</hi> as for Example, the <hi>Tiger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Prize,</hi> from the 1ſt of <hi>October,</hi> 1692, which is <hi>ſix Years laſt October,</hi> and abundance more of above <hi>ſix Years ſtanding,</hi> and the <hi>Suffolk,</hi> St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> and about 40 <hi>Ships</hi> more never paid off their <hi>Recalls</hi> ſince the 1ſt of <hi>October,</hi> or thereabouts, in the <hi>Year</hi> 1693, which is above <hi>five Years unpaid,</hi> and that I may make the <hi>Ruinouſneſs of the Pay to be plain to any one thar can but tell their Fingers and Thumbs, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear how much worſe and dreadful Ruinous it will be, if extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Care be not taken to Pay them with Speed, Honour, and Honeſty;</hi> and this I would repeſent as beforeſaid, admitting, as is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, that the mony due at <hi>October</hi> 1697, and the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal pay ariſing before the 1ſt of <hi>October</hi> 1698. to be 22 <hi>hundred Thouſand Pound,</hi> and ſuppoſe there was paid between the 1ſt of <hi>October</hi> 1697, and the 1ſt of <hi>October</hi> 1698 in that Year <hi>five hundred and twenty five Thouſand Pound,</hi> that is but one quarter, and will be 4 Years in <hi>Paying,</hi> that is as many <hi>Years</hi> as I have <hi>Fingers on my Right-Hand.</hi> But now, ſuppoſe there be now in 4 Years more but <hi>two hundred Thouſand Pound,</hi> the <hi>Year</hi> following Pay it will be near <hi>Three Millions</hi> of Money in all, and at <hi>Five hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pound</hi> the Year, will be above 4 Years more before the <hi>Fleet</hi> will be paid clear off; and if we conſider how dreadful it will be for thoſe many <hi>Thouſands, and Ten Thouſands,</hi> who have pay due <hi>five or ſix</hi> Years already, to ſtay <hi>three or four Years</hi> more before they are paid, that will make it up <hi>eight or nine Years.</hi> But it may be ſome will ſay, <hi>That if the firſt paid, it may be but one with another about five Years, and let the reſt ſtand, as ſeveral Ships Books will teſtifie of late;</hi> and indeed, for eleven Ships kept in Pay at <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> that have between <hi>three and four hundred thouſand Pound due for Wages,</hi> and if there be but <hi>Five hundred Thouſand Pound</hi> the year paid, theſe Ships will take up great part of one Years Money, and what muſt Pay the reſt of the <hi>twenty Ships at Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> beſides <hi>Chatham,</hi> and beſides all that are in the <hi>Rivers,</hi> or at <hi>Sea?</hi> how miſerable muſt their Caſes be, and how miſerable thoſe many times <hi>ten Thouſands</hi> of the <hi>Old Pay</hi> on the <hi>Recalls,</hi> which none knows when they will be ſo much as pretended to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62670:6"/>be paid, and it may be ſome will ſay, <hi>What do I mean to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be paid?</hi> to that I will ſhew them ſome Years in which <hi>the pretended Payments</hi> fell <hi>dreadful ſhort,</hi> and I do not write as many do, out of <hi>Fancy,</hi> or <hi>Prejudice,</hi> what I cannot prove; but I will <hi>prove</hi> what I <hi>write of the Ruin of the Seamens Pay, by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ships Books, if his Majeſty pleaſes, and it ſhall not coſt him Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence;</hi> and as to <hi>Pretended Payments,</hi> the <hi>firſt was in the Year of our Lord,</hi> 1692, <hi>That bleſſed Year that we did Beat the</hi> French; <hi>but wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable have the Dreadful Ruins been ſince, for their Paying was ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for ſeveral Months, and the Ships not Recall'd for Payment as they bad been of other Years, ſoon after the coming on from paying on Board.</hi> But however, in <hi>October</hi> 1692, about the <hi>Sitting of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, there was a brave Show put up at the Pay-Office of</hi> 166 <hi>Ships to be Paid; but after ſome Flouriſh therein, the waiting of ſome Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and ten Thouſands Weekly, and Monthly for their Pay, there was no' above one Quarter of them paid all the Year, as I did humbly Repreſent to the two moſt Honourable Houſes of Parliament in Print the next Year, and gave away about</hi> 500 <hi>Printed Accounts to them freely, but Sold not any one about the Town, and the Honourable Houſes were pleaſed to Order a great Relief the next Year in their Payment, although there were abundance of other Miſeries thrown on them of which I Repreſented about twenty ſeveral Sorts, and alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented how, and by what ſeveral Methods His Majeſty and the Nation was Cheated in many Caſes, which I ſuppoſed, if prevented, would have ſaved above a Hundred Thouſand Pounds the Year; and gave away four Sheets apiece in Print to great part of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Members of both Houſes, but Sold none; for I hid from the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men their miſerable Miſeries in the Lump, that as they knew them ſingly, ſo they might groan and Mourn ſingly, without Diſturbance.</hi> But their <hi>Ruins</hi> increaſing, I humbly Preſumed to Repreſent their <hi>Miſerable Caſes</hi> to the Honourable Houſes, in the <hi>Year of Our Lord, 1695,</hi> and gave away 500 Books of four Sheets each, to the Members of both <hi>Houſes,</hi> wherein there were Thirty ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Miſeries Repreſented, and I gave the Honourable Members between Three and four Hundred Books of about Eight Sheets apiece, of Ways and Means to Relieve the <hi>Seamen,</hi> and prevent <hi>His Majeſty</hi>'s being Shamefully <hi>Cheated,</hi> and the <hi>Seamen</hi> Cheated and Abuſed alſo; beſides that, I gave the ſame Year about Four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Books of four <hi>Sheets and an half of</hi> Paper to the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Members about the <hi>Coin,</hi> and to propoſe the Raiſing Money,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62670:7"/>by Four Millions of Bills, and all this at my own <hi>Charge,</hi> not having <hi>one Penny Aſſiſtance from any one Alive towards the ſame, neither in Money, neither any Aſſiſtance from any in the Writing of one half Sheet of Paper, and I Bleſs God, who enabled me to be true and Faithful to my King and Country therein, and that the</hi> Honourable Houſes <hi>paſſed by my Infirmities in the ſame, from firſt to laſt; and now I ſpeak of Bills, makes me to think once more with how much eaſe the Seamen might be all paid off with Honour and honeſty, with Exchequer Bills before</hi> May-day <hi>next, if the Houſes would raiſe three Millions of Exchequer-Bills, as before Repreſented, and the Seamen need not be continued to be more and more Ruined from Year to Year, by lingring, pretended Payments, ſuch as the Liſt put up; alſo in</hi> Auguſt, 1697, <hi>A while before the Parliament ſate; but as I ſaid before, above a Hundred Ships Payments dropped to this day; and of the Ships that were paid off laſt Winter, the Recalls have not been ſo much as pretended to be put up for Payment; and of thoſe Ships that have been kept needleſly in Pay a Year and a Quarter, I ſuppoſe it hath Coſt the</hi> Nation <hi>about</hi> Five or Six <hi>hundred</hi> Thouſand Pounds <hi>Extraordinary Charge to keep them from beng paid off, beſides the dreadful Ruin of the Seamen, and their Families, and thoſe who had truſted them before on the Credit of their Pay; for many of thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Wretebes had Tickets given them for their Pay, and ſold them, ſome at</hi> 7 <hi>or</hi> 8 <hi>or</hi> 10 <hi>Shillings in the Pound Loſs, and ſo could not Pay their Debts; and as the Extortioners, ſome of them ſwallowed-half their</hi> Pay, and the poor Wretches ſo Ragged and miſerable, many of them looking more like <hi>Captives,</hi> taken by an Enemy, than Loving, and Faithful <hi>Subjects,</hi> ſerving their King and Country, as thoſe who uſe to go on <hi>Board</hi> of Ships have ſeen the Men ſo Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as if they had come out of <hi>France,</hi> and had on the old Cloaths that the <hi>French</hi> had given them. But this by the way, I ſay, <hi>The Extortioners getting by their Tickets one half, and the Furniſhing them out again fit to ſave their Lives, and do their Work, by being Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Men, or Chriſtians; there has been a poor little left for their Families, if any, and ſometimes none to Pay their Debts;</hi> ſo that the badneſs of the <hi>Pay</hi> hath been the way to <hi>Ruin the Men, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi> and to <hi>Cheat, and Ruin them that Truſt them;</hi> Beſides, as I ſaid, the Extraordinary needleſs <hi>Charge</hi> to <hi>His Majeſty.</hi> But I intend to <hi>Repreſent ſeveral Reaſons</hi> for their being honeſtly and ſpeedily Paid; and I remember a Story I have read of a great <hi>Courtier,</hi> I think it was <hi>Cardinal Woolſey</hi> That after he had long ſerved
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62670:7"/>his King, was brought to Ruin, and he had this Expreſſion, <hi>If he had ſerved God as induſtriouſly and Faithfully as he had ſerved the King, he would not have Ruined him at laſt.</hi> And now I ſpeak of the Holy Name of God, there doth come a place of Scripture into my Mind, and it is in the firſt of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the 2d, and the 9th. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither hath it entred into the Heart of Man the things which God hath prepared for them that Love him. And on the contrary, I fear I may ſay,</hi> Eye hath not ſeen, neither hath Ear heard, neither can it enter into the heart of Man, to Conceive the Miſeries, and Ruins, and Deſtructions, and Poverty, and Groans, and Cries of thoſe Seamen who have loved His Majeſty, and their own Native Countries, and loſt their Health and Lives, and many Thouſands of them their Pay alſo for their Serving both; <hi>And indeed, I will be plain-Hearted, I have often thought, that if the Devil, and the Jeſuits, and the Late King's Friends in</hi> France <hi>and</hi> England <hi>had ſate in Council about the Loyal and Faithful Seamen of</hi> England <hi>after they had beat the</hi> French, <hi>and had ſaid in the Sea-Dialect, Theſe eternal damn'd Dogs the Seamen of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland <hi>will fight like Dragons to keep out a Popiſh Religion, and French Power, and we can never have a Ship or two betrayed to us, except privately, becauſe theſe damn'd Dogs the Seamen are ready to defend their Ships, and their Nation, let them loſe never ſo many Lives; therefore we muſt conſult how to Ruin them ſome other way; for to endeavour to ruin them them by fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, would Ruin all the French Seamen, and all the French Ships; therefore we will endeavour to Ruin them twice over another way, and three times over another way, and they ſhall run the Hazard of being Ruined five times over another a chird way, and that is as many times over as a Man hath Fingers and Thumbs on his Hands; but we muſt endeavour to bide the Method, or at leaſt, the Knowledg of it, from their King and Parliament, and then it may be it will coſt the Nation ſome Millions of Money extraordinary to Ruin them; but it muſt be pretended they are managed to the beſt Advantage, and, if they be kept turn'd from Ship to Ship, and not paid off till they fall ſick, and die like ſo many Rotten Sheep, until ſeveral Ships Books will prove they have been Manned over their Number of Men</hi> 8 <hi>or</hi> 9 <hi>times before they have been Paid, and that they have Buried twice, or near thrice their Number of Men before they have been paid, and yet though it is the Experience of many Years, that when Ships are kept unpaid three or four Years, the Salt Victuals, and Salt Air,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62670:8"/>and hardſhip, and want of coming on Shoar for freſh Air, and freſh Proviſions, there commonly died the greateſt part of their Men, and the that Captain</hi> St. Loe, <hi>one of His Majeſties Captains, and Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, Repreſented in Print ſome Years paſt, thht the Nation might have ſaved five hundred Thouſand Pound a Year by paying the great Ships every Winter, and yet he ſaid, We might have kept out at Sea all the Winter, fiſteen Third Rates, and eight Fourth Rates, beſides fifth and ſixth Rate Ships, and have ſaved many Thouſand Pounds in the Year; beſides this being repreſonted by me ſome Years paſt among the Ways to ſave the Seamens Lives, and the Nations needleſs Charge; yet they have been kept on Board their Ships, or been turn'd from Ship to Ship, until there hath been the Loſs of above</hi> 60 <hi>Thouſand of their Lives, as the Ships Books will prove, and that is twice the Number, that, as I remember, the Parliament ſaid was a</hi> quota <hi>for the Fleet, that being thirty Thouſand ſtated by them, for a Year, and there being above a</hi> Hundred Thouſand of the miſerable Seamen <hi>run out of their Pay, as the ſeveral Ships Books will prove, which is</hi> Thirty Thouſand Payments ruined three times over; <hi>And alſo, as there is about</hi> an hundred and fifty Thouſand Payments <hi>more due, that are not made Run. If they are not Paid before the Seamen by lingring now on Shore have Spent it, or take Tickets, and ſell for half Loſs, or what they can get, and ſo murder their Pay, and ſtarve their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, or Cheat and Ruin their Creditors, it will be a way to have five times more a</hi> Stroak of Ruin, if not many knocked down with it. But I ſay, had theſe things been contrived by our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the Enemies of God and Goodneſs, aforeſaid, and had been known openly, it would have been prevented; <hi>But being carried on by pretended Friends, and by pretended Policy, we have loſt five times more Seamens Lives this War, and that the moſt part without Fighting, than ever was Loſt at Sea by Fighting in the moſt Bloody War that ever was; although, when our Nation was at War with the</hi> Dutch, <hi>in</hi> 1666. <hi>Our Commanders and Ships fought againſt the</hi> Dutch <hi>like ſo many Furies, ſome of them as if the Devil and the Jeſuits had laid a Plot to Eſtabliſh the Proteſtant Religion by the ſpuiling and deſtroying of two of the moſt Potent Proteſtant Nations, Ships and Seamen.</hi> But now in this War, we have had ſuch ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous running away from the <hi>French</hi> at Sea, as if a Proteſtant Church was to be eſtabliſhed by letting the moſt violent, perſecuting People on the Face of the Earth crow over us; and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62670:8"/>although Bleſſed be God, that Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> did, with our Fleet, Beat the <hi>French</hi> Couragiouſly, that they could never dare to fight us ſince; yet our Loyal, and faithful, couragious, but miſerable Seamen, have been more Ruined ſince than any <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> I could ever <hi>Read of, or Parallel;</hi> and I do think, as I ſaid before, we have loſt more <hi>Seamens Lives</hi> without Fighting, than was ever loſt in our <hi>Engliſh Fleet</hi> fighting, ſince the days of <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> and therefore, as I am a going to render ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the <hi>Seamens</hi> being honeſtly and timely paid; this may be, the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That as their Ruin and Deſtruction have been more in the Service of this Government, than under any King or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in theſe Nations; therefore, in Honour, Honeſty, and Juſtice, they ſhould now be honeſtly and ſpeedily Paid what is due to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To let their Families Periſh now for want of their Pay, would be againſt <hi>Grace, and Reaſon, and Common Sence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Their Pay being ſo Prodigious great, can never be Paid while the World ſtandeth, except there be Money Raiſed on purpoſe by the <hi>King and Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Their Pay being, as beforeſaid, due great part for ſeveral Years, and it hath been a dreadful Caſe to let the Ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Periſhing Families live on Credit, or Starve ſo long, and if it be ſeveral Years more, as it muſt be, without a conſiderable Supply, it will be not only like <hi>Miſery to Miſery, but like Cruelty to Miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Tho there be ſome millions of Money due to others in <hi>England</hi> beſides the Seamen, yet it's moſt either to thoſe who have Intereſt for it, or have gotten a great deal of it, if not all, by the Government, and it is well, if ſome have not Cheated for half of it; but as I ſaid, they have greateſt part Intereſt for it. But the intereſt that the poor <hi>Seamen</hi> have, is, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them Rags and Lice, and Poverty, and Miſery to them, and the Starving, and Periſhing of their Ruined Families, that have no Money, neither now at laſt any Credit; and if they have, they Pay perhaps ten in the Hundred more than others, and this, and their Cries and Groans to God, Angels, and Men, has ſuch Intereſt as the miſerable Seamen meet withal for lying out of their Money for their Faithful, and Loving Serving this Government.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62670:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The lettings of the <hi>Seamen</hi> be Ruined, and Periſh more under this Government, than they ever did in any Age of the World in ſo few Years, ſeem to Croſs the very end and deſign of Gods raiſing up this Government, which was for to deliver us from miſery and ſlavery, and make us happy and ſafe, and proſperous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> We cannot in a probable way be either ſafe or hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in theſe Nations, without the help and aſſiſtance of the <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and one would think neither <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> nor <hi>Jacobites,</hi> nor <hi>Men,</hi> nor <hi>Devils,</hi> could prevail upon us, to run and deſtroy, and Ruin the <hi>Seamen</hi> and their Families more than needs muſt; when it is in our Power to pay them, however, at laſt, their juſt due.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> His Majeſty hath ſpoken for them ſeveral times, and tho' he did not Name them in his laſt Speech, yet he Nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the National Debts, of which there is no doubt, but he was willing that they ſhould be paid alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Both the King and Parliament, and Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have Recorded them to be ſuch, as the ſtrength and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe Nations, and all His Majeſties Dominions doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon, and what Madneſs would it be to Impoveriſh and Ruin ſuch, as our happineſs and ſafety ſo much depends upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> The King and Parliament have, as aforeſaid, declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they have diſtinguiſhed themſelves throughout the World, by their Induſtry, Diligence and Skilfulneſs in their Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and by their Courage and Conſtancy, for the Defence and Honour of theſe Nations; and what a Crying ſin adn ſhame would it be to let ſuch Periſh for want of their Pay, as the whole World admires for their braveries?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> His Majeſty and the Parliament as aforeſaid, hath declared that if they and their Families fall under hardſhips and miſery, they ſhould be Relieved at the Publick Charge, and if ſo, then how dreadful would it be, if inſtead of being relieved by the publick, they ſhould be more Ruined by the publick, by waiting, many Ten Thouſands of them Year after Year longer, for what is due in ſome Years paſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> The Ruin of them and their Families is againſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence, for common ſence will tell any Man in <hi>England,</hi> that his Dogs or Horſes muſt have Food or Periſh, and if the <hi>Seamens</hi> Families have neither Money nor Credit, they muſt Starve or be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62670:9"/>Relieved by the <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> and I do not find that when poor wretched <hi>Seamens</hi> Families, have been kept unpaid 4 or 5 <hi>Years,</hi> and it may be, one or two of their Children are Periſhed, that the Pariſhes are ready to relieve the reſt, but will rather be ready to ſay, <hi>What! ask Relief, and have</hi> 50 <hi>or</hi> 60 l, <hi>due.</hi> It hath grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved my very Soul to ſee the Tears and Cries of ſome of them in their Miſery, and if they would have hanged themſelves, could not get their own; and how crying a Sin, and Shame this is, I appeal to God and Man, and if theſe Nations lets them run the hazard of their Periſhing worſe than they would their Dogs, and Horſes, how dreaful will that be; and indeed, I think the <hi>Seamens</hi> Families are many times as dreadful Objects of <hi>Miſery,</hi> as moſt in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was a going to write ſome Particulars of their <hi>Miſeries,</hi> by Reaſon of their lying out of their Honeſt, Juſt Pay. 4, 5, or 6 <hi>Years;</hi> but I will not write a Volume as big as the <hi>Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> concerning the dreadfullneſs of their Ruin; but inſtead of that, I remember the Church of <hi>England Catechiſm,</hi> my good old gracious Mother, Taught me near fifty <hi>Years</hi> paſt, <hi>To do to all as I would they ſhould do unto me;</hi> and thus every one in <hi>England</hi> that is Catechized according to the Order of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is bound to own; and therefore in the <hi>Thirteenth Place;</hi> If any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in <hi>England</hi> would willingly be kept out of their Right, and not have one Penny of Money in 4, 5, 6, or 7 <hi>Years,</hi> to keep their Families from Periſhing, then with a ſafe conſcience they may be Content that the Seamens Families ſhould be ſo ſerved; But if the Gentry would not be kept out of their <hi>Rights</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Years, neither the Clergy out of their Tithes ſeveral Years, and run the hazard of Starving their Families, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how they can pretend to Teach their Children this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and will not keep it themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourteenth</hi> place. Though it may be I ſhall be complained of for my ſpeaking ſo much for the Ruined Seamens Families be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Relieved, yet I will bring this as another Argument, That all the Lords, Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and,</hi> are bound by the Churches Order in Prayer in the Litany, to beg of God on <hi>Sundays, Wedneſdays,</hi> and <hi>Fridays,</hi> that God would pleaſe to Succour, and help, and Comfort all that are in Danger, Neceſſity, and Tribulation, and that God would defend, and provide for the Fatherleſs Children, and Widows, and all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62670:10"/>that are deſolate and oppreſſed; and I would not be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable as to think, that ſo Honourable Perſons will go to mock God with Praying for that they care not ſhould be brought to paſs; and I am ſure it is not my Duty to Pray for any other to Relieve, and Comfort, and provide for the Ruined Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, their Fatherleſs, and Widows, but only this Government, that they have ſerved; for I do declare before God and the World, that if it be pretended by others to relieve thoſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined Creatures, they would be in danger of deſtroying <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> at Land, before they relieve thoſe at Sea. But indeed, I will be plain-hearted, to ſay, in the Preſence of the ever Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, before I whom I write every Word, and leave it as a</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifteenth</hi> Agument. That ſeeing the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> have ſerved their own Native Country, and loſt 60 <hi>Thouſand Lives</hi> in that Faithful Service, and defence of their Country, if this Government at laſt, by the Reaſon of ſo many Villains Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Couzening and Undermining of them, had been overthrown, yet it had been a dreadful ſin and Shame to the Nation it ſelf, to have ſuffered the Loyal Seamen to Periſh, and their Families to be ruined for want of their Juſt and Honeſt Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixteenth.</hi> I would appeal to the Reverend <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the Houſe of Lords, whether, if theſe <hi>Nations</hi> ſtarve and ruin the Begger'd, miſerable Seamen and their Families for want of their Juſt Payment, it be not a more crying Sin than one of <hi>Sodom's</hi> Sins, ſpoken of in the 16th <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 49th and 50th verſes, where God ſaid to his profeſſing Church and People, by his Prophet; <hi>Theſe were the Sins of thy Siſter</hi> Sodom, <hi>Pride Idleneſs, fullneſs of Bread, and that ſhe did not ſtrengthen hands of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Poor and Needy.</hi> Now if theſe were the Sins of <hi>Sodom</hi> that She did not ſtrengthen the hands of the Poor, and Needy, how much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sin muſt it be to ſtarve, and Begger, and ruin the poor an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Needy, by keeping them out of their juſt Wages and Dues many Sums of which were earned with the Loſs of Lives. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was not ſaid of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that She Employed Thouſands of po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and miſerable Wretches to defend the Place they did belong to and would not Pay them in time; but if <hi>Sodom</hi> did not ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Mercy to the Poor and Needy, whether, if poor Ruined Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mens Families be left to Starve and Periſh ſeveral Years with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62670:10"/>out their honeſt Pay, the Sin of <hi>Eugland</hi> will not as far exceed <hi>Sodoms,</hi> as Injuſtice and Cruelty exceeds Unmercifulneſs. And therefore Juſtice and Mercy will have that the Seamen of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> do require a ſpeedy and honeſt Payment. But it may be ſome will ſay, that <hi>Sodom</hi> was guilty of Beaſtly Luſt beſides, which is ſeldom ſeen in <hi>England;</hi> but to that it may be anſwered, That it is to be feared it is practiſed too much in <hi>England,</hi> witneſs one Sea Captain, which ſtood in the Pil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory thrice this Week for attempting it ſo groſly; but if there be not ſo much of that as was in <hi>Sodom,</hi> it may be feared that there is ten times more Lewdneſs with Women in <hi>London</hi> it ſelf, than was in <hi>Sodom,</hi> and if one ſhould ſay, there is as many deſtroyed in <hi>London</hi> by Fire from Hell in three or four Years, as was in <hi>Sodom</hi> by fire from Heaven; it may be ſome would think I was Mad; but to put that out of doubt, they that will read the Yearly Bills of Mortality, may find that in ſome years paſt, there was near a hundred Perſons in a Year dyed of the French-Pox; and if it be true as a Phyſician hath Printed, that there is near ten times as many dye of it that are not ſet down to dye of that Diſeaſe, but of Conſumptions, or other Diſeaſes; then it may be ſuppoſed there is near a Thouſand People the Year dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Bills of Mortality that are conſumed by Fire, which ſhews that the Judgments of God are not at an end in the World; and if one ſhould imagine how many there are that Eſcape, and get Cur'd, if they could be numbred up, it would be a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous number of filthineſs that is Committed in <hi>London and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and we may dread the <hi>Hand of God</hi> againſt theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> for this, or for <hi>other Sins;</hi> and the Reaſon why I do Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent this, being out of the Way of <hi>Seamens Payment,</hi> is, becauſe, <hi>it may be, ſome of the Fathers of the Church may conſider of the Crying Voice of this Sin before God, and of the Thouſands, and Ten Thouſands of Families Beggered and Ruined, and of the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Lovely Young-men that are drawn in by Lewd Women, and Corrupted in Body and Souls; many have been Rotten before they have been Ripe, and the Youth of the Nation, and the Flower of the age being in danger of Ruin, and I do believe it would be very acceptable to God and Man, to have Laws made to Tranſport all thoſe Lewd Women away to the Plantations for Slaves all their days, and to cut off the firſt Joynt of their Little-Finger for a Mark, and if ever they returned again to</hi> England, <hi>to hang them up, and to Confiſcate the Eſtate of every Maſter of a Ship that ſhould dare to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62670:11"/>bring any of them back again.</hi> And for the Puniſhment of the Men Offenders, no doubt but there may be ways found out to make them <hi>Examples,</hi> and if they do not <hi>Reform,</hi> ſend them away alſo; for if it be <hi>a dreadful thing</hi> for a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> or others, to have their Sons Murthered, how much more <hi>Dreadful muſt it be to have Bodies and Souls alſo Murthered by thoſe Day and Night-walkers, who, like their Maſter, the Devil, walk about ſeeking whom they may devour;</hi> and the dying at the Gallows commonly own Lewd Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be the cauſe and incouragement to bring them to <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> as their <hi>Wickedneſs doth unto the Gallows;</hi> But in all <hi>Chriſtian Likelihood,</hi> the <hi>Judgments of God will teach theſe Nations by ſome dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Stroak to Reform, and amend;</hi> And whoever Reads but the Word of God, need never look after other ſorts of <hi>Propheſy</hi> to tell him, <hi>That theſe Nations that know more than ever Iſrael did, may expect to ſuffer the Correction of God, altho in what manner God alone knoweth, to whom I leave all that hath been ſaid by me, or I ſhall ſay, and ſhall come to another Reaſon, why the poor Ruined Seamen ſhould be paid with all poſſible ſpeed,</hi> and that is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventeenth.</hi> His moſt <hi>Gracious Majeſty</hi> hath been pleaſed to ſpeak to have the <hi>Cauſe of the Poor in general, minded;</hi> and although he did not name the <hi>Seamen</hi> in Particular, yet I know no poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>miſerable, and ruined Objects in England than many Seamens Families are; and if keeping miſerable Creatures out of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney four, five ſix, or ſeven, Years be a cauſe of Poverty, then here are many ten thouſands of Poor to be minded, Relieved, and paid before they Periſh quite. And again,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighteenth,</hi> I would appeal to all the <hi>Reverend Biſhops,</hi> if the <hi>Sins of England,</hi> if they let the <hi>Seamen,</hi> or their <hi>Families</hi> to periſh for want of their Pay, will not be worſe than the <hi>Sin of Dives;</hi> for <hi>Dives's</hi> was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmercifullneſs;</hi> it is not ſaid of <hi>Dives,</hi> that he employed poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> to defend him, and work for him till he fell Lame, and Sick, and then let him <hi>Periſh</hi> for want of his <hi>Honeſt, Juſt Pay,</hi> for we do not Read he owed him any thing but <hi>Charity;</hi> and we Read of <hi>Dives's Dogs,</hi> they licked poor <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus's</hi> Sores, and did not ſnap and ſnarl at him when he asked <hi>Charity;</hi> And I will declare in the <hi>Preſence of the Lord Jehovah,</hi> before whom I write, that I have often thought that thoſe who ſnap and ſnarl at the poor <hi>Ruined Seamens Widows, Wives, or aged Parents,</hi> when they come to the <hi>Navy-Office</hi> to get Curſed unjuſt Q. and <hi>R.</hi> off, or to ask for their <hi>due Debts,</hi> that they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62670:11"/>who ſnap at them, do not ſhew themſelves ſuch <hi>Loving, humble natured Creatures as Dives's Dogs. But God grant that the Seamen may be paid off, that they need trouble them no more, and</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nineteenth, again, Seeing there is about a Hundred Thouſand of Payments of their Wages ſtripped from them by thoſe two dreadful fatal Letters,</hi> O. R. <hi>and that there is two or three hundred poor miſerable Wretches forced now to the Admiralty-Office daily, to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, or loſe their Money. It is pitty that the other hundred and fifty Thouſand Payments ſhould be kept from them till they periſh for want of that. Alſo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twentieth, Seeing ſo many Thouſands of them have waited ſo many Years, and the Ships pretended to be paid, although not one Man in Four of ſome of thoſe Ships paid; it is pitty that the reſt ſhould wait ſeveral Years more for their Money. And the</hi> Prophet Jeremiah, <hi>Lamentations</hi> 4, and 6. ſaith, <hi>That the the Sea monſters did draw out their Breaſts, and give Suck to their Young ones; But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>The Daughter of my People is become Cruel, like</hi> Oſtriches <hi>in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs.</hi> Now it ſeems 'tis the Nature of the <hi>hardened Oſtriches,</hi> they leave their Eggs in the Sand, that the Foot may Cruſh them, or the Wild Beaſt break them, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, 39, and 14. 7, 5. But ſaith <hi>Job; She is hardened againſt her Young, becauſe God hath deprived her of Wiſdom;</hi> and the Lord grant our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Seamens diſtreſſed Wives, Widows, Friends, or Relations may not be ſlighted as the <hi>Oſtrich</hi> ſlighteth her Eggs, and that for the time to come, the Seamen ſhould be kept in any Ships until they dye like <hi>Rotten Sheep,</hi> for want of freſh Air, and freſh Proviſion; and there be at laſt many ſet aſhoar Sick, and the <hi>Ships</hi> go away, and leave them; But it may be conſidered thoſe poor <hi>Wretches</hi> might dye ſome of them, or continue long Sick, and could not go on Board of their <hi>Ships;</hi> and therefore it is pity that <hi>the Beaſt ſhould tread their Pay to Death, or the Wild Beaſt break it with thoſe fatal Letters,</hi> Q. R. <hi>when they do not deſerve it, and that Thouſands have not deſerved it the Certificates will ſkew, for the taking them off again; and as I ſaid, thoſe ſeveral Hundreds wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for more to be taken off.</hi> And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twenty One.</hi> God himſelf, who cannot Lye, hath ſaid, <hi>Malachi 3.5. That he will come and be a ſwift Witneſs againſt thoſe who do Oppreſs the Hireling in his Wages, the Widows, and the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and turn aſide the Strnger from his Right in the Gate.</hi> And James 2, 1ſt and 4th verſes. <hi>Go to now ye Rich Men, weep, and howl
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62670:12"/>for the Miſeries that ſhall come on you. Behold the Hire of the Labourers, which is of you kept back by Fraud, Cryeth, and the Cries of them that have Laboured, are entred into the Ears of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And under the Old Law, the <hi>Jews</hi> were Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God to be ſure to Pay their Labourers Wages at Night, and their <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Servants and Strangers were Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be ſpeedily Paid; and if <hi>Iſrael</hi> were to be ſo juſt in Paying the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> if they ſerved for Money, although the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> had made <hi>Iſrael</hi> Slaves before; then how ſad will it be to let our Seamens Wages be any more Years unpaid, who have helped to keep all theſe Nations out of worſe Slavery than <hi>Aegyptian Slavery,</hi> as much as Soul-Slavery is worſe than Body-Slavery. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twenty two.</hi> It is ſaid by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>That the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure we met ſhall be meted to us again.</hi> And this is repeated in the Goſpel more than once, and if that Chriſt ſhould make theſe Words to be accompliſhed on theſe Nations, or the Land, that the Inhabitants at Land ſhould be as miſerably deſtroyed in their Lives, and kept out of their Rights as many Years as the Seamen have been out of their Pay, they would think it the miſerableſt ſtarving Condition that ever the Nation did groan under; and if the Biſhops and Clergy in <hi>England</hi> were to be kept out of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues and Tythes, 4, 5, or 6 Years, and not have one Penny to buy a Penny-Loaf for their Wives and Families for ſeveral years, how could their Wives and Children keep from periſhing; as many of the Seamen have three or four Children apiece, and how any Men of Sence can think they can buy Cloaths to keep their Bodies from Periſhing, while they ſerve their King and Country, and Bread to keep their Families from Starving, I cannot imagine; I do ſuppoſe if the Clergy were kept out of their Tythes but two or three Years, they would cry out of Sacriledge and Oppreſſion, and no body knows what; but when they hear of the Dreadful Ruins of theſe miſerable Creatures, their Fellow-Subjects, who have loſt ſo many Thouſands of Lives to keep the Clergy of <hi>England</hi> from being Slaves to the Beaſt, yet they can hold their Tongues, and hardly repreſent it to the Magiſtracy as any Sin; neither to tell them whether all the Oppreſſions that the Prophets of Old did Complain of againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> did exceed the miſerable Death, Deſtruction, and Ruin that hath fallen on, or been thrown upon the Loyal and Faithful <hi>Seamen of England,</hi> and it might be a Queſtion whether ever thoſe Rulers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that were
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62670:12"/>by the Prophet called Roaring Lyons, and Evening Wolves, <hi>and that did gnaw the Bones till the Marrow, did ever tear ſo much from the poor miſerable</hi> Iſraelites <hi>in any one Age, as hath been torn from the Ruined Seamen of</hi> England <hi>in thoſe hundred Thouſand</hi> Q's and R's, <hi>on the the one hand, and it may be, a Hundred Thunſand of Payments on the other hand ſold for a Third Loſs ſome, a Half Loſs others, and two Thirds Loſs to the Devil's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-pieces of Extortion, the Ticket Buyers.</hi> And, as if twelve Shillings in the Pound were not enough for the poor Ragged, Begger'd, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined Seamen to loſe, the Devil hath helped his Servants, the Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners in ſome Sea-port Places far from <hi>London,</hi> to take their Tickets of forty or fifty Pound, and lend them ſix or ſeven Pound, and take a Bill of Sale for the whole Money, and if they redeem not their Tickets in a little time, then the Extortioner will have it all. O Lord! it makes me ſigh to think to what a dreadful, Shameful heighth of Villany the Extortioners are come to on the other hand; and if that Crying Sin of Extortion, and Unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs, and perverting the Judgment of the Stranger, the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and Widows, thoſe three Curſed Sins that the whole Church is bound to Curſe the Authors of, in the Book of <hi>Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they being ſuch Crying Sins, I ſay if they continue Sins ſtill, and that the Cuſtom of them in this Age hath not taken away the Conſcience of them; then what dreadful Judgments may theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions expect, without Repentance; and I might defie all Hiſtory to ſhew where any Nation,</hi> Jews, Turks, or Heathens, ever did exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe greater Extortion than hath been exerciſed on the Seamens Pay, and if that any will ſay, yes, <hi>Jezebel</hi> took away <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bath's</hi> Vineyard from him for nothing, and indeed that was true; but ſhe did not oppreſs him ſo long until he was forced to Sell it for a third part, to buy Bread and Cloaths; But ſecondly, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel</hi> was a Fool to the leaſt Captain, or Captain's Clerk, or Clerk at the <hi>Navy-Office,</hi> for Power to take away all a Man hath by ſetting on Letter <hi>R.</hi> upon his Name, and it is gone without ſhewing any Cauſe or Reaſon in the World. But the quickeſt, wholeſale Work with running the Seamen out of their Pay, was within a few Weeks after they came aſhoar, when they had beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the <hi>French,</hi> then they were made all <hi>Run,</hi> 2 or 300 in a Ship, which was wholeſale Work. I have ſeen one Captain's Book, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there were about 300 made <hi>Run</hi> at that time, and I heard one that was his Clerk, ſay, That he ſwore in Vexation, and cried,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62670:13"/>
               <hi>Damn it, ay, they will Run me at laſt;</hi> but in the <hi>next Spring</hi> they took off many of thoſe <hi>R</hi>'s: But inſtead of giving the poor <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Bounty-Money</hi> in the <hi>Spring,</hi> as they uſed to have before they beat the <hi>French,</hi> they were many of them abated three or four Pound a Man out of their <hi>Pay,</hi> beſides all other <hi>Miſeries</hi> thrown on them after they beat the <hi>French,</hi> from ſome of which I wiſh they ever get clear; and therefore as they have ſuffered ſo much ſince they beat the <hi>French,</hi> and prevented the <hi>French</hi>'s having an opportunity to ruin the <hi>Nation and Clergy</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and bring in their <hi>Popiſh Idolatrous Maſs,</hi> and <hi>Cruel, Bloody Perſecution;</hi> and therefore thoſe <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> that are aquainted with thoſe that are in Authority, may do well to ſhew them whether there be ſuch a <hi>Sin</hi> now in this Age as <hi>Oppreſſion and Extortion,</hi> and if there be not, then whether there be not one part of the <hi>Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets laid aſide.</hi> Although our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour ſaith, <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away before one Tittle of the Law do paſs away;</hi> and if Oppreſſion and Extortion be a <hi>Crying Sin,</hi> then it is the Nation's Duty to relieve them by Juſtice and Mercy, and to puniſh the Extortioners; and if ever theſe Nations would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Reformation, I do believe God will expect that there ſhould be ſome way appointed for to enquire into all thoſe who have bought, or cheated the poor Hirelings Wages for half Loſs, or more; and if there were a <hi>Committee</hi> to be appointed to hear the Caſe, and Relieve all the Seamen, or their Families, that have Sold their Pay for 4, or at moſt, above 5 Shillings the Pound loſs, and make the Buyers make Reſtitution; it might diſcover Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion enough, it may be, to make our Ears to tingle, and if the Clergy will not ſpeak a word for to help forward this, I will in Love and Friendſhip ſpeak a word in Humbleneſs to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Reformation; and for the firſt, that I may keep up the Honour of the Miniſtry, I will ſay, we have as ſober, induſtrious Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> many of them, as in moſt Nations in the Chriſtian World, and it is the Sober and Pious Miniſters helps yet to keep up the Honour of the Profeſſion of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> But I would have it obſerved alſo, that as it was in <hi>Iſrael</hi> God's only Church and People in the World; that there were ſome that were as good Figgs, very good, and ſome Figgs ſtark naught, and good for nothing, except to make a Stink, as the <hi>Prophet</hi> plainly ſaith, that from the Prieſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs was gone forth in all the Land.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62670:13"/>
            <p>And this I would ſay, <hi>That if ever there be any true Reformation in</hi> England, <hi>there muſt be a Reformation of the Miniſters as well as of the People; and without there be a Reformation, the Laws of God, and the Doctrine of the Church, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le Word of God from</hi> Geneſis <hi>to the</hi> Revelations, <hi>will ſhew us, That we muſt expect Ruining Judgments: For the Scripture ſuth, Righteouſneſs exalts a Nation, but Sin is a Ruine to any People: And Chriſt ſaid to the Prophecying</hi> Jews, <hi>That except they did Repent, they ſhould all likewiſe Periſh.</hi> How this comes into theſe Sheets about the <hi>Seamens Ruine,</hi> but that <hi>God Almighty</hi> led me to Write of it: and that <hi>God</hi> led me to Write what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and God will bring what I write to Judgment, and all the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Ruins and Deſtructions to Judgment, and all the Accounts that hath been ſo publickly given of the <hi>King's</hi> being ſo ſhamefully Cheated, and Miſerable Seamens being Cheated, as hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented for ſome Years by ſuch poor Fooliſh Creatures as were Mr. <hi>Crosfeild,</hi> Mr. <hi>Trever,</hi> and Mr: <hi>Baſtion,</hi> which laſt are gone to Eternity, and are ſilent in the Grave; and for Mr. <hi>Crosfeild,</hi> ſince he ſaw that all he could do in offering to prove ſo much Cheating as he did, could not prevail for him to be heard; I think he is ſilent in his Habitation, where-ever it is, having not ſeen him as I know of, this Twelve Months; and for my ſelf (<hi>the moſt Feoliſh of them all) God Almighty</hi> is pleaſed to enable me, and ſtir me up, to put theſe Nations in mind of the moſt Dreadful, Ruined, Dying, Deſtroyed Caſe of the Loyal <hi>Engliſh and Scotch Seamens Lives, Health, and Pay:</hi> And this brings to my Mind, the Words that was ſaid of the whole <hi>Earth</hi> before the <hi>Flood, That it was filled with Violence; God grant that it may not be ſaid of theſe Nations before the Judgments of God break out upon us, That the whole Sea Affairs were filled with Violence, and that after the Loſs of above Sixty Thouſand of the Lives of ſuch who were kept hound to their Ships until Sickneſs came; or Death took them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and then alſo there was a violent Order to Q. and R. all thoſe from Receiving their Pay, who was ſet on Shoar Sick to ſave their Lives, and above an Hundred Thouſand Seamen Bun out of their Pay, and yet no certain Rule made, how to Relieve and Save their Pay to themſelves, or Periſhing Families, neither any one Man can be ſafe to ſerve his King and Country for time to come without hazarding the Looſing his Pay, and Ruining of his Family; if he falls Sick, and is ſet on Shoar Sick, and the Ship goes away, and leaves him, and he cannot get on Board again, or continues Sick, or Lame half a Year, or a Year; or if Well, goes on Beard of another Ship; or if Dead, and it may be his Friends not knowing how
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62670:14"/>as when he Died, and ſo his Wife and Children looſes his Pay; I would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all Mankind, If there be not a Care taken to ſecure their Pay bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when Sickneſs, or Lameneſs come, and ſome Rational Rules laid down and ordered, that they may in caſe of Sickneſs, or Lameneſs, have their Pay ſecured, how any Man can ever for time to come be ſafe in ſerving at that dreadful uncertain rate of management, ſince they are no more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of their Health and Strength and Lives, than the Beaſt of the Field; and I do think no Chriſtian, or good Natur'd Heathens, would have their Cattle turned out of their Provender for every Sickneſs or Lameneſs, and ſtarved, if they cannot come to work again in twenty eight Days time. But this moſt dreadful violence was powred upon the Seamen after they beat the</hi> French, <hi>for they were Paid when ſet ſick on ſhore before they beat the</hi> French, <hi>as the ſeveral Ships Books will prove that were paid, before they beat the</hi> French, <hi>and paid off alſo when they came in at</hi> Michaelmas, <hi>before they beat the</hi> French, <hi>the great Ships Companies were paid, But when once they had beat the</hi> French <hi>and put a ſtop to their Carreer, then there was a ſtop put to their Payment in the great Ships as before; But indeed, it might be endleſs for me to write the Multitudes of the miſeries of them and their Families ſince. But I may ſay, as the Prophet of old, concerning the deſtruction of</hi> Iſrael <hi>at Land, ſo of our Seamens Ruin and Deſtruction at Sea and Land both:</hi> O! that my Head were Waters and mine Eyes a Fountain of Tears, that I might Weep Day and Night, for the ſlain of the Daughter of my People: <hi>But to have done with that which makes my heart to ake while I write it. I think, we at Land pretend to a greal deal of Liberty and Property, and ſo we have, Praiſed be the Lord; But as to the Poor Ruined Seamen of</hi> England, <hi>no Hiſtory in the World can ſhew ſuch a Hiſtory of the loſs of our Seamens Liberties, Propertiez and Lives, in the Service of their King and Countrey, in any Hundred Years, as hath been theſe laſt Nine Years. A Man could hardly imagine their Lives and Pay ſhould be ſo ſcambled away, but that the Ships Books will prove it at the</hi> Navy-Office, <hi>and they may be Regiſter'd to help to fill a dreadful Hiſtory in the next Age, when it is like, they will write plainly how the Seamen were begger'd and ruin'd in this. And how Impudently, and Shamefully, and Scandalouſly, the King and Nation was cheated, and how the Cheats and Villains were excuſed, and thoſe that would have brought their Villany to Light were diſcouraged, and how the Knaves and Extertioners, and Cheats got Eſtates, while the King and the Nation was Cheated, and the Poor Trampled on and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62670:14"/>Ruined by Thouſands;</hi> And now methinks I remember ſomething that I dreamed of as I lay in my Bed, of the laſt age; and this I thought, that when as King <hi>Charles.</hi> II. came home again to <hi>England</hi> in 1660. There was as it were a ſtrange Race begun, and continued many Years, <hi>would God it were at an end;</hi> and this was the Race methought the Devil run, and the Jeſuits run, and the drunken, lewd, ſcandalous Prieſts began to Run, and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns were all to debauch and prophane, and poiſon theſe Nations with Lewdneſs, for two Deſigns, the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> to bring the <hi>Nation</hi> to <hi>Popery</hi> when they had debauched away their Religion, and the drunken Prieſts to keep their <hi>Preferments and Livings,</hi> and looſneſs alſo, without fear or danger of any <hi>Reformation;</hi> and methought they went a great way, and had two Idols, an Elder Brother, and a Younger; the one Idol for Lewdneſs and Prophanenſs, and the other for Idolatry, and the old Whore at <hi>Rome.</hi> But the firſt Idol not going ſo far and faſt towards <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Jeſuits would have him, he went out of the World few knows how; <hi>and then came the other</hi> Idol <hi>in Play, and be poor</hi> Soul <hi>run ſo faſt, that be tumbled down and broke his Head, and in getting up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, had only Wit enough left, and Courage enough to run away, and happy was it for the Nation he had not more</hi> Wit, or Courage, <hi>for it was to be feared he would have been a ſad Plague to the</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>if he had ſtaid; but by his Running, the</hi> Jeſuits <hi>loſt the rarity of their Show that they intended to act, if they had not been kick'd off from the Stage; and now it may be, ſome will ask if this Race be at an end, to that I would anſwer,</hi> I fear there is too much of it under hand; <hi>and if any ſhould ask me;</hi> who the Devil did pick up of late for Company, <hi>to that I would anſwer,</hi> That I think the Drunken Prieſts keep him Company ſtill; <hi>and they are ſo Vile, that 'tis a Mercy they do not make the Church ſtink of them in the Noſtrils of God, and of Good Men. But if the two Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſes make that moſt Excellent Act againſt</hi> Immorality and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanneſs, <hi>I hope they will order thoſe of the Clergy that are guilty of thoſe Sins to be puniſhed, and turned out of the Church; for if they do not, I do fear, nay, I think I might lay my ſelf down at the Feet of the King and Parliament, and ſay,</hi> That I will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſuffer any Pnniſhment, or any Death you will put me to, if God Almighty does not ſpew out theſe Wretches him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, unleſs they amend, <hi>or the Law of the Land throw them out. God knows why I ſhould write this, for I do from my Heart Honour
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62670:15"/>the Miniſtry as an Ordinance of God, and I honour all the Good and Vertuous in that profeſſion, by what Name ſoever they are Called; and they are called Aagels,</hi> and their Office is from God, but the Sins of the Lewd ones are from the Devil; <hi>and it is ſaid, That if Angels fall, they turn Divels; there is one of them hath been ſo Shameleſs as to Print a Book in defence of Concubinage, which is ſo Shameleſs to write a Book in defence of that which the whole Church is bound to Curſe every</hi> Aſh-Wedneſday, <hi>and therefore ſuch Wretches ought to be ſeverely puniſhed. And now as to the Company which the Divil hath pickt up of late to run with him, I think that he hath got, beſides the Drunken Prieſts, abundance of Cheats, and Knaves, and Extortioners, and Ticket-buyers, that Swallow the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Pay at 8 or 10, or 12 Shillings in the Pound Loſs, and could Stock-job and buy the Wages of the poor Labourers at the Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Office at ten Shillings and Sixpence in the Pound, and then have for 85 Pound 100 Pound, and the King Pay a Hundred Pound Tally for Eighty five Pound, that is allowing fifteen in the Hundred and ſeven in the hundred Intereſt, is an Hundred and Seven Pound, for forty five Pound in one Year, ſo the Poor loſt forty ſeven in the Hundred, and the King paid twenty two in the Hundred, and who would but ſtretch his Conſcience on the Tenter-Hooks to get ſuch a Carſed deal of Money out of the Poor; but the King and Nation pay more than all a great deal at laſt, and the</hi> Victualling-Office <hi>could not help it neither; they bad not Money, that the Poor were kept ſo long out of their Money, that many of them did ſell for what the Extortioners would give; God knows what an Age we live in; when I read how dreadfully God threatned, and Scourged the</hi> Jews, <hi>for their Extortion, Oppreſſion, trampling on the Poor, and their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, I know not what to ſay to the Genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion we live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong; but I do think ſome do act as if they were like the</hi> Jews <hi>of Old, in ſaying,</hi> tuſh, God ſeeth not, God hath forſaken the Earth. <hi>But certainly God Almighty doth expect that the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhould be Relieved, and the Extortioners puniſhed, and if all that have extorted above 4 s. or at moſt 5 s. in the Pound out of the Pay or Wages of the Scamen or others, were made to pay back again 2 s. to the Poor Oppreſſed for every Shilling Extorted above that, it would be the way to help and relieve the Oppreſſed, and it may be one Reaſon why many that are to receive large Sums of the Seamens Pay, are Content to let it linger on by degrees, may be, becauſe if they are paid one Thouſand out of four Thouſand in a Year, they may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62670:15"/>lay out that, and buy eighteen hundred, or Two Thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſo get 7 or 800 Pound the Year three or four Years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the Seamens Miſeries; but to have done with that, I would Humbly propoſe and entreat the Honourable Houſes of Parliament to Relieve the Seamen by paying them ſpeedily, and to Relieve many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them, and their Families, by altering part of the Acts of Parliament, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lled</hi> Acts for their Incouragment, <hi>for the following. Firſt,</hi> for God's Sake. <hi>Second,</hi> For the King's Sake. <hi>Third,</hi> For the Nation's Sake. <hi>Fourth,</hi> For the Sake of the Seamen and their Families.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, For God's Sake, and becauſe I an to ſpeak of His moſt Holy, and Glorious Name, I ought to ſpeak with ten-fold the Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and therefore will leave it to the Reverend Clergy to conſider firſt if Holy</hi> David, <hi>who was not only a King, but one after God's own Heart, and he would not offer to God of what coſt him nothing, though he might have had it given him by the Right Owner, and a Rich Man as</hi> Aurana <hi>allows;</hi> and how much ſadder is it for theſe Nations when they are to incourage the Seamen to take 6 <hi>d.</hi> a Month out of the Miſerable on one part of our Loyal Seamen to raiſe Money to help to gratifie, or ſhew Charity to the other. But it is ſaid by <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of Kings, <hi>That he that doth mock the poor reproacheth his Maker.</hi> Now, whether it be not a mocking of our poor and miſerable Seamen, to make ſo many poor and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Labourers pay ſixpence a Month out of their Hire, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards advancing Encouragement for the others, and the others have had not one Penny of the 40 <hi>s.</hi> the Year paid them as I hear of to this Hour, although the Act for to make the other Pay hath been about two Years in Force. But 3dly, The ſaid <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that taketh from the Poor to give to the Rich, ſhall come to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty:</hi> Now, if it be ſo, that all the poor Seamen that are not Regiſtred have 6 <hi>d.</hi> the Month taken from them, and the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred have not had two pence of it in two Years; But there are ſeveral Commiſſioners, and Clerks have ſome Hundreds a Year for their Sallary to Live Great, and not the poor miſerable Seamen that are Regiſtred; is not this taking from the the poor, and advancing of the Rich, and therefore as God is a Holy, and Juſt, and Merciful God, who always pities the Poor, I would beg that our poor Seamen might be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tied for His Sake, and have nothing taken out of their Pay more than ever was in any Age of the World; for God alſo knows they have loſt more Lives,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62670:16"/>and Pay, under this Govern neat, than ever they did in any Age of the World; and God knows they have ſhewed themſelves as Loving and faithful to this Government, as to any Government in the World, and now 4thly, As God did by His Providence Raiſe up his Majeſty to be means, under God, to reſtore theſe Nations to their Liberties and Freedom, whether it will not be a going contrary to the very Providence and end of God in raiſing up this Government, if, inſtead of Liberty and Freedom the poor and miſerable Seamen, whoſe Bones, and Lives have been as Walls to keep this Government, and the Nation from Ruin; If one part of them ſhould be perpetually bound, and the other pay continually towards keeping them; ſo then, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that will not be ſad. But now, 5thly, I would beg there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for His Majeſty's Sake, that he would let the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> be as free all of them, in their Service and Payment, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being perpetual Bondmen, or Paying Money perpetually out of their Pay, and ſeeing the worſt of Kings that Reigned in <hi>England</hi> never let them be bound or entangled in their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Payment, God forbid they ſhould be more entangled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the beſt of Kings; and eſpecially ſince they have loſt more Lives and Pay under His Majeſty in his Service, than under any four Kings in their Grand Fleets. 2dly, I would for his Majeſty's Sake, beg, that as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Raiſed her Pay from 14 <hi>s.</hi> the Month, to Eighteen, and the Long Parliament from 18 <hi>s.</hi> to 22 <hi>s.</hi> the Month, for their incouragement; ſo his Majeſty, when he ſhall have occaſion to have them Fight for him and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion again, would Raiſe their Pay two or three Shillings the Month, and Pay them well, and they will fight to the laſt drop of their Blood for him, and in the mean time never let it ſtand upon Record that their Pay was abated 6 d. the Month in his time, and eſpecially, ſeeing, as I ſaid, the Reſt have not been 2 d the better for the ſame; but inſtead of that, the King was brought into Debt, as I remember the Houſe of Commons Repreſented laſt <hi>March,</hi> Nineteen Thouſand Pound in Debt upon account of the <hi>Regiſter Office,</hi> and the Seamen pay for it, and neither the King nor the Seamen the better, it will be hard; and I could never find that it ſaved the King twopence Charges in preſſing Men in the War, neither ſave him a Groat Charge ſince. Therefore I would for his Majeſty's Sake, wiſh with all my <hi>Heart</hi> that His Majeſty was ſet free from his Extraordinary
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62670:16"/>needleſs Charge, and the Seamen from their extraordinary need-Payments, or Bondage. But now, 3dly. I would for the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Sake beg that there might be ſome of the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment altered about the Seamen, ſince Trading is bad, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney hard to Raiſe; and to be at an exceſſive needleſs Charge for Offices, and Officers, except it were of great Advantage to the King and Nation, I think it were better to lay it aſide. But 4thly. If the Nation had a real Mind to Encourage the Seamen, they might do it without ſo much charge of Tax on the <hi>Seamen,</hi> to maintain Offices, and Officers, which God knows whether all the poor <hi>Seamens Sixpences</hi> the Month will much more than maintain that Grandeur, and incumbrance, and never known ſort of <hi>Office or Officers;</hi> for when there was a Mind to Reward the <hi>Officers the Fleet</hi> after that ſhameful keeping our <hi>Smyrna Fleet</hi> near 3 <hi>Maths</hi> at extraordinary needleſs Pay, until juſt the <hi>French Fleet</hi> was ready to go out, when our Fleet might have gone out 2 Months ſooner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with an Oyſter Smack for their Convoy, there being Men of War, and Merchants Ships enough in the <hi>Smyrna Fleet</hi> to have gone through the World, before we waited until the <hi>Grand Fleet</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> was ready, and then when our Fleet was fool'd in the Mouths of their Fleet, then after that our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers had a <hi>Bounty</hi> of about 60 or 70 Thouſand Pound the Year double Pay ſettled on em, and never troubled themſelves for an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> for it, but ordered it, and paid it, and never cauſed the <hi>Parliament</hi> to make one part help to Relieve the other; but as I ſaid, gave them 60 or 70 Thouſand Pound the Year, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Nation was at that time in exceeding Streights for to raiſe Money, and had loſt in about one Years time, as near as I could eſtimate, about 3 <hi>Million of Riches</hi> in <hi>Eaſt India, Guinea, and multitudes of other other Ships, and</hi> Streights <hi>Ships loſt, or fooled into the Hands of the</hi> French, <hi>and therefore God, Angels, and Men might ſee how the Nation could ſquander away Money to the Rich, or Officers needleſsly, by Thouſands and Ten Thouſands, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ten Thouſands; but whether to one Penny advantage to the King I could never ſee, hear, or underſtand. For my part, if I had been a Commander of a Man of War, and had run up and down ſeveral Years and never hurt an Enemy, or protected a friend;</hi> I ſhould have thought it brave Encouragement to run fooling up and down, and never Fight, and have a hundred, or two Hundred a Year extraordinary, and I ſhould have thought <hi>Cowardice</hi> was better
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62670:17"/>rewarded now, than <hi>Valour</hi> was heretofore; although indeed here tofore if there were <hi>Rewards and Honour,</hi> it was uſed always to be Conferred on <hi>Courage, valour,</hi> and <hi>Merit.</hi> But indeed there was no need of <hi>double Pay</hi> for the Officers this War, except for run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up and down from <hi>Port to Port,</hi> and Lying ſeveral Months in <hi>Port,</hi> and never doing any good, which was Chargeable for the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers that came ſo much daily on <hi>Shoar,</hi> when, as the poor miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Seamen</hi> were kept <hi>on Board,</hi> and were ſometimes 30 or 40 in a Ship Sick in a Week; but they dyed and periſhed for want of coming on <hi>Shore,</hi> and being <hi>Paid, as in other Ages</hi> Beſides <hi>hundreds and thouſands</hi> who fell ſick or died <hi>with eating bad victauls preſently after they ſerved this Government;</hi> and it was but putting the King and Nation to about 50 or 60 <hi>Thouſand Pound the Year extraordinary Charge, to preſs more, as it coſt the Nation by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner St.</hi> Loes <hi>Rule near</hi> 500 <hi>Thouſand Pound the Year, needleſs Charge, for want of Paying off the great Ships that might have been ſpared all the Winter; ſo that one might admire how the Nation Scam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled away Money ſome ways, and how poor and miſerable it was in the Caſe of the poor Seamen, that they muſt one part help out of their Poverty, to encourage the other part to continue Bondmen.</hi> But now, for the Nations Sake, that they may not think the encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Thirty Thouſand Seamen could ſave the King any thing, or incourage all the Seamen of <hi>England</hi> to come into the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; I will undertake to prove by the ſeveral Ships Books that for above ſeven Years together there were above Thirty Thouſand either dead, or ſet on Shoar Sick, or run out of their Pay, or diſcharged out of the Fleet; and I would appeal to all Mankind, at Seven Years end, which of theſe Thirty Thouſands muſt be the true and only 30 Thouſand to be encouraged, ſince the King had in that time, in all Likelihood 5 or 6 times thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Thouſand in his Service, and as there was above twice thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Thouſand dead this War, and near four times thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand run out of their Pay, it would require ſomething of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in the Regiſter-Office to pick out the right thirty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; and yet it may be ſome will ſay, they would endeavour to find out all the reſt of the poor miſerable Souls, and they, or their Widows ſhould be ſure to be abated 6 d. the Month out of their Pay; If the thirty Thouſand got not one Groat Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance-Money: and therefore now I will beg for the poor and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Seamens ſakes, that the ſix pence the Month may not any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62670:17"/>longer be ſtopped out of their Pay; for if we conſider their pay is ſmall, and their hazard and Charge is great, they go now in Merchants Ships for 22 s. or 23 <hi>s.</hi> the Month. Now ſuppoſe they lye at home but one Month in a Year, and have half pay for a Month more, there is ten Months pay at 22 <hi>s.</hi> is 11 <hi>l.</hi> and one Month at 11 <hi>s.</hi> Now ſuppoſe at their coming home, they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, as many do, near a quarter of their Pay for damage, or what ſhall I ſay, becauſe the poor miſerable Fools went to <hi>Sea</hi> in old Rotten <hi>Ships,</hi> ready to drown them; and ſo out of 11 <hi>l.</hi> 11 <hi>s.</hi> they have about nine Pound, out of this there muſt go Five Shillings and Six Pence, to Relieve their Poor Diſtreſſed Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and they muſt have Cloaths and Bedding, and as they muſt many times be as wet as drowned Rats two or three times a Day, muſt have Cloaths to ſhift them, or run the hazard of being unable to perform their work, ſo it will take up about three or four Pound a Year for Cloaths, and reckon but Twenty Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a Man for Expences, or Brandy to carry to Sea, there will be about Five Pound the Year left to keep their Families, and that is not a Groat a day, and many of them have three or four Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren apiece, and the 6 <hi>d.</hi> a Month taken out of their Pay, would buy two or three Bullocks Hearts, or Sheeps Heads, and a peck Loaf for their Families; ſeeing alſo ſometimes the poor <hi>Seamen</hi> meets with <hi>Loſt Voyages,</hi> and ſo are ſet back in the World more miſerably than other poor Wretches; and therefore as all the Labouring Men in <hi>England</hi> are at Liberty, without paying any Tax out of their Wages; God forbid but the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould be leſt to as much freedom to take all their Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges themſelves, without being the only objects of Miſery in War, and taxing in Peace, more than any ſort of People at Land, for in all <hi>Land-Taxes,</hi> their <hi>Families</hi> are liable to pay with the reſt of the People, and it hath made my Heart ake to think how they could pay the Taxes for their Landlords, 4 <hi>s.</hi> in the Pound, or for their <hi>Births, or Burials,</hi> when their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands have not been Paid in four or five Year, and for my own part, I having been intruſted laſt Year to gather the whole Tax for our Liberty, have laid out for ſeveral, both laſt year, and this year, rather than take away that poor ſorry Goods they had; and ſome of them have not enough to Pay their Landlord's Tax if they were bound to be hanged for it; therefore I did look on it as Charity to them, and Service to the King, to be Patient to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62670:18"/>them, and lay down the <hi>Money</hi> my ſelf, and make the <hi>Government eaſy</hi> as I could, and though I do now lye out of ſome <hi>Pounds</hi> that I paid in ſo the King laſt year, I never did get 2 <hi>d.</hi> by it, neither ever ſhall; but I think often of good <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Word in driving his Cattel, <hi>That they muſt be driven as they could go, leſt they ſhould Dye:</hi> Would God there had been more Care taken in the driving of our Seamen this War, and that when it was ſeen they dyed ſo faſt in keeping ſo long turned from Ship to Ship without liberty of freſh Air, and freſh Proviſion, until they died like Rotten Sheep, for ought I know, it might have ſaved a third part of their Lives if they had come on Shoar Yearly, and been paid, as the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> did their Seamen; I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that, though the <hi>French</hi> was at War againſt our Fleet, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet, that he hath been at 6 Millions of leſs Charge for his Fleet than we theſe laſt 10 Years; and I ſuppoſe the <hi>Dutch</hi> hath ſaved near 8 Millions of Money in the Charge of their Fleet theſe laſt 10 Years; and methinks I have often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd at it, that the work of this laſt Age hath been more five times to ſtudy how to raiſe Money, than how to ſave it; but I ſuppoſe if it had been truly ſtudied how to ſave it, then ſo many could not have been maintained to live ſo Idly, and ſo great, neither could have gotten ſuch Eſtates; and if we had a fourth part more of Ships, and Officers imployed more than needs, or the great Ships kept in Pay in the Winter, when Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain St. <hi>Loe</hi> ſaid there might have have been <hi>five hundred Thouſand Pound a Year ſaved by it;</hi> But then the Officers could not have lived ſo great, and one trick I remember, becauſe there was Money plenty enough for to ſcamble away among the double-Pay Officers, the Officers were kept in Pay one Winter in the great Ships, and the Seamen diſcharged, and to be ſure we had no need to Preſs Captains and Lieutenants next Year, and one would admire that when a Nation hath ſo much Money to laviſh out for Officers needleſsly that at laſt if the Seamen are but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to be Relieved, or to be incouraged, they muſt pay 6 <hi>d.</hi> the Month out of their Pay towards it. But it may be ſome will ſay, now the Regiſtred Seamen are to be preferred to Offices; but I remember the words of the Act ſaith, <hi>They that are Officers, muſt be ſuch as are Regiſtred;</hi> but doth not ſay they muſt have been Regiſtred a Month before they are Preferred, which makes my Windmill-working Thoughts Ramble as far as <hi>Rome,</hi> where
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62670:18"/>none muſt be Pope but a Cardinal, and none a Cardinal, but a Prieſt. Now, I ſuppoſe there may be as many Prieſts in the Roman Teritories of all ſorts, as is Seamen in <hi>England,</hi> and very few Prieſts proffered to be Cardinals; but inſtead of that, if any King, or Prince, or the Emperor hath an old Swearing, Whoring General to prefer, and can get the old Father the Pope, in whoſe Breaſt Preferments lye, to accept of this debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed General for a Cardinal, and to give him a Hat, he can quickly be qualified, as follows, firſt make him a Deacon one Week, then a Prieſt another Week, then a Cardinal afterward, and the hundred and fifty Thouſand Prieſts look as ſimply as they did before; ſo with all humble ſubmiſſion would I ſay, If in <hi>England</hi> for time to come, that Debauchery, and Lewdneſs, and Prophaneneſs ſhould keep on its Courſe, and the Laws of the Land, or ſome exceeding Providence, or Judgment from God do not put a ſtop to that Flood of Wickedneſs now running, then I might ſuppoſe if a Gentleman had a Son that had lived in Swearing, Whoring, and Debauchery until his Father was afraid he would come to the Gallows, and to prevent that, ſend him to Sea Three Months to know the Head of the Ship from the Stern, and how to Swear and Damn after the Sea Mode, as he did after the Land mode, and then get him Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and make Friends to prefer him to be a Lieutenant, and then if he never ſerved his King and Country Ten Months order him double Pay, and let the Seamen that have been Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred 10 or 15 Years, if any of them be left alive ſo long, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at it, and let them if they pleaſe to buy a little Book put out about the Lottery called, <hi>The Fools Expectation,</hi> where there was one Lot gained to make a Noiſe, and 20 Thouſand loſt to make it good; but to have done with that, I would hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg, that the Regiſtring our Seamen may be taken off, and the 6 <hi>d.</hi> the Month from the others that are to pay it, and if any ſhould ſay that the Act of Parliament ſaith they ſhall not be diſcharged their Ship, or turned over before they are paid, To that I would anſwer, <hi>There was an Order this Year to diſcharge all that would out of ſeveral Ships, and give them Tickets for their Pay, and inſtead of turning over of Seamen into other Ships, the way was to ſend them forty, or fifty into other Ships to go out and do the Work of the other Ships, and then come back to their own, which is ſuch an incouragement as I fear our Country Plow-boys would not like:</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62670:19"/>if their Maſters ſhould ſay, <hi>Be Good Boys, I will not turn you away, neither put you out of the Service of my Houſe before you are paid, but you ſhall do my Work, and go and do the Work of Captain ſuch a one, and Captain ſuch a one; and if you ſerve two or three Maſters, and do haſten the Work, you ſhall be paid before you are let go; tho you ſtay ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years for it, as it is ſaid the Dutch Captain did for a Wind.</hi> Now this is a very homely Compariſon, but I moſt humbly beg pardon for this, and all my Failings; and indeed in one part I ſhall puniſh my ſelf, for a great deal being to pay for all I Write, the more Charge out of my own Pocket for Printing; and being to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven away, make no advantage of it to my ſelf; for if the Seamen are Ruined and Deſtroyed in War twice more than needs, and Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd and Impoveriſh'd in Peace, I have indeavoured in ſome Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs from firſt to laſt to Repreſent their Caſe, and I hope as I have been willing to be at the continual Charge for <hi>God's ſake, and the King's ſake, and the Nations ſake to indeavour their Relief, I hope God of his Infinite Mercy will keep off the Guilt from me of her need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Death, ſhameful Miſery, and being ſcandalouſly Oppreſſed, Begger'd, Cheated, and Ruined; and I do humbly leave my ſelf, and what I Write, and all my Family, and all my Affairs, into the Hands of the Eternal Love and Mercy of our moſt Gracious God and Father, in and through Jeſus Chriſt his only Son, and our only Saviour and Redeemer for all Times and all Eternity,</hi> Amen. And now having ſaid, that I ſhould hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly make bold to repreſent ſome few things to the Nation, that I ſuppoſe may be to their exceeding Advantage; and the firſt would be for the Temporal and Eternal Happineſs of the Inhabitants of theſe Nations: That is, Firſt, <hi>That there might be all care imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make ſuch Laws as may ſeverely puniſh Whoredom, Drunkenneſs, and Extortion, and all manner of Vice and Sabbath-breaking, which Sins thoſe at the Gallows commonly complain; doth help to bring them to their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntimely Ends, and therefore thoſe Laws might be heartily and effectually put in execution:</hi> For it cannot be ſuppoſed by any Conſiderate Man that hath read and underſtood the Scripture, but that there muſt be <hi>Reformation</hi> or <hi>Ruine</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> And Secondly, <hi>There muſt be a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and Reformation of the Clergy, as well as the Laiety;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>Honeſt Sober Church of</hi> England <hi>Men and Women,</hi> are ſadly to be lamented in ſeveral places, that have ſuch Lewd, Debauch'd, Ignorant Wretches forced on them for their Teachers, that are a Scandal to the Name of <hi>Church Miniſters;</hi> and certainly God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will in few Years ſpew them out, and therefore they were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62670:19"/>be Reformed or turned out by Law firſt, that they may not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the Ruine of that Church they pretend unto; for God will not long be mocked, with the empty Name of the <hi>Temple of the Lord;</hi> the Temple of the Lord; like the <hi>Jews</hi> of old, which the Prophet ſpeaks of, who ſaid to them, <hi>Will you Steal and Murder, commit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, and Swear falſly and then come and ſtand before me in this Houſe, and ſay, We are delivered from all theſe Abominations,</hi> Jerem. 7.9, 15. But ſaid God, <hi>I will caſt you out of my Sight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And one thing I would obſerve, That the great Ruine of the <hi>Jews</hi> began after they had been under one of the beſt of Kings, as <hi>Joſiah</hi> was; for tho he was ſo good, the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> was ſo moſt dreadfully over-run with Wickedneſs under their other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wicked Kings, that both Princes, Elders, Prieſts and People, were ſo wicked, that the Wrath of God did come on them, and there was no Remedy; and among all their other Sins, their oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Poor, and treading on the Poor, was one great Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; and as they had the moſt Light and Mercy of any Nation of the Earth, ſo God made them to know how dreadful a thing it was to ſin againſt that Light: And if they could not eſcape the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, that ſinned againſt that Light, how much more ſadly will the Sins of <hi>England</hi> call for Judgment, if we do go on in all manner of Abominations, both againſt the Light of the Law and the Goſpel? And indeed, God is the ſame God Yeſterday, to Day, and for ever; and therefore I do believe we may conclude there will be no Remedy for theſe poor Nations, but <hi>Reformation</hi> or <hi>Ruine:</hi> And indeed we have ſome ſad Symptoms on us already, that great Dearth of all ſorts of Proviſions, and that ſad deadneſs of Trade in the City and Nation, and our Scarcity of Money ſeems to me, as if God were threatning ſuch a Judgment to us as to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, to be as a Moth to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and as Rottenneſs: Now a Moth Conſumeth ſecretly, and Rottenneſs goeth before Breaking; and I do not know that I ever heard of more breaking than of late; and as many of our Seamen have ſold their Pay for 10 or 12 Shillings in the Pound loſs, ſo many Thouſands have been paid their Debts at Land with 12 or 15 Shillings, or more loſs in the Pound; and as above 100 Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Seamen are run out of their Pay with <hi>Q.</hi> and <hi>R,</hi> ſo it may be ſuppoſed above 100 Thouſand Debts at Land have been paid with nothing but bits of Paper to Diſcharge them; and as our Seamen have ſtay'd ſeveral Years for their Pay, ſo it may be there have been two Millions or more of Debts at Land compounded for time, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62670:20"/>it may be moſt of it for ſeveral Years, and if this be ſad, how ſad would it be if God ſhould ſay to <hi>England</hi> as he did to <hi>Iſrael, That he would be as a Lyon to us, to tear and rend us, and go from us:</hi> That would be dreadful, and therefore there had need be very ſevere Laws, and to be ſeverely put in execution againſt all manner of Whoring, Blaſpheming, Debauchery and Profaneneſs: And what may God ſay of this Nation, when he ſhall ſee that in the laſt Age, when there were Laws made againſt his Worſhip in theſe Nations, that they were made ſo ſevere, and put ſo ſeverely in execution, that they ruined many Thouſands of Families, and great Multitudes loſt their Lives in Priſon, among which I remember were four Miniſters in one Year died in <hi>Newgate;</hi> among which, was Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> as I remember, that was like to have been Hanged before King <hi>Charles</hi> came in, for his and Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s endeavouring to bring King <hi>Charles</hi> in; and after he was in, he let him periſh in a Jayl for all that, and ſuch, or much worſe Rewards I ſuppoſe muſt thoſe dull Souls expect who would bring that Judgment upon the Nation, of having the late King <hi>James</hi> again: But I will only put them in mind of thoſe dreadful Objects of Miſery the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who helped to ſupport the <hi>French</hi> King to the Throne, when he was in danger to be put by. But this is a Diverſion, and now as to what I was to ſpeak of concerning God's ſeeing with what Zeal, may I not ſay Rage and Fury the Laws were made and executed in the laſt Age a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſolemn Worſhip and Service; and if there be neither Zeal nor Courage or make Laws, and put them in ſevere execution againſt Whoring and all Debauchery; in this will it not appear before God, Angels, and all Men, that the laſt Age was five times more ſevere againſt the Service of God, then this is againſt the Service of the Devil; and that tho the laſt Age puniſhed and baniſhed thoſe that Worſhipped God; but this is backward in puniſhment, and more ready to protect than baniſh thoſe who do help to ſpoil, and poiſon, and infect this Nation with their accurſed Sins, and that the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of this Day, are accurſed by the Judgment of the whole Church, and that the Church hath cried out above 140 Years <hi>to have them that were guilty of Notorious Sins to be puniſhed openly, that others might take warning by them, as any that will read the Preamble to the Commination in the</hi> Common-Prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>which they carry to Church, may find, and that in the mean time they ordered the whole Church in their Solemn Service to Curſe abundance of Crying Sinners, as Idolaters, Adulterers, Extortioners and ſuch as ſmite their Neighbour ſecretly, or remove their Landmarks,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62670:20"/>or are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmerciful, or pervert the Judgment of the Poor, the Fatherleſs, and W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ddows, and ſeveral other Sins; I wiſh ſome of thoſe who manage our Brave, Couragious, Loyal, but Begger'd and Ruined Seamen of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>be not guilty of earning abundance of theſe Curſes, when they put by the Poor, Fatherleſs, and Widows, from their Receiving of their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, or Childrens Pay by thoſe fatal Letters</hi> Q. R. <hi>when they have loſt their Health and Strength in the Service of their King and Country, and are ſet on Shoar Sick, and it may be Die there, there is no Method found out how to ſecure their Pay, but if they live</hi> 100 <hi>or</hi> 200 <hi>Miles from</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>they muſt come or ſend, and prove, and have Certificates, and I know not what Waiting, to get that which God, Angels, and Men knows is a dreadful Sin, and Shame, and Plague to keep them from it, and it may be this helps the Poor Miſerable Wretches to wait</hi> 150, <hi>or</hi> 200 <hi>on a Day, ſometimes at the</hi> Admiralty <hi>for Relief:</hi> But this by the way, <hi>It may be ſome will think I ſay too much of it, but for ought I know I may ſay, If God doth not avenge this by ſome Judgment on the Actors, on this Nation, that God hath not ſpoken by me.</hi> But now to return to the Propoſal of ſevere Laws againſt the Debauchery of the Age, the laſt Age did uſe Impriſonment and Baniſhment for the puniſhing of the Worſhippers of God, and if this Age do not Impriſon and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh a Multitude of the Whores and Villains of this Age, for ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Devil, and Poxing, and Debauching, and Ruining the Youth of the Nation, it will be to be admired at, ſeeing that indeed if De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery and Lewdneſs be not puniſhed and prevented, but that it increaſeth as much more in the next Age as it did the laſt, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be a very Peſt-Houſe of the Plague Sores of Sin; and it is to be feared the Sound will have much to do to ſupport themſelves and Families againſt Cheats and Villanies, and Curſed Wretches who are likely to poiſon their Children, Servants. Friends, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, that we are like to be as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, before their Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who the Prophet ſaid was full of Wounds, and Bruiſes, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified Sores, and it will be well if ſome of the Inferiour Magiſtrates be not in time corrupted, that will be ſad.</p>
            <p>I remember a Story of an Honeſt Country Parſon that was preaching to a Corporation in the Country, on the choice of a Mayor, and he ſaid, <hi>Magiſtrates was called Gods.</hi> Now, ſaith he, <hi>as they are called Gods, you ſhould take care you do not chooſe a drunken God, or a Whoring; unclean God.</hi> Now he might have took the Cemmon-Prayer Book, and ſaid, for all his being a God, If that he be ſuch a one, the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> is bound to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62670:21"/>Curſe him out the Year, therefore for that thing; and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſons, I would beg that that the deſire of the Common Prayer that hath ſtood there about 140 years might now be in ſome <hi>meaſure granted,</hi> and all thoſe ſort of Sinners ſeverely puniſhed, and the Curſes taken clean out of the Book, and that the poor may be relieved, and now I come to that again, I would hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg that the <hi>Ships</hi> for time to come might be paid in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> where the poor <hi>Seamen</hi> have been forced to be aſſiſted, and ſupported all this War, when they had no Money nor Cloaths to fit them for the <hi>Sea,</hi> or when <hi>Twenty, or Thirty Thouſand</hi> of them were taken Captives into <hi>France:</hi> Then they came to the City of <hi>London</hi> for Supply, and as the City hath always been rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to aſſiſt the Government with Money, and the Seamen with Neceſſaries, and their periſhing Families with Bread for ſeveral Years, while they Earn'd their Money; and were not paid; and that now therefore they might be paid in <hi>London,</hi> where they may buy their things at the beſt hand, and have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to return their Money to any Part of <hi>England</hi> to their Families, and the King need not be at extraordinary Charge to ſend Money, and Clerks, and Commiſſioners 40 or 60 Miles to pay them in a ſmall Town or two; but the King might ſave that Charge, and much more to pay them in <hi>London,</hi> in this Method fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: <hi>Suppoſe a Ship of</hi> 300 <hi>Men be ordered to be Paid at</hi> Ports<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>or</hi> Chatham, <hi>fourteen Days hence, it may be it is ten days before the Money and Commiſſioners get down. Now ſuppoſe theſe</hi> 300 <hi>Men, Officers and all Goſt the King but</hi> 2 <hi>s. a day apiece, victuals and Wages, that is One Pound a Man for ten Days, is</hi> 300 l. <hi>Now ſuppoſe an Order is ſent down to Clear them off to Morrow, and give eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man</hi> 5 s. <hi>to Travel to</hi> London, <hi>is</hi> 75 l. <hi>And pay them at the ten Days end, the King will ſave</hi> 225 l. <hi>in a Ship, beſides travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Charges, and they that Live in</hi> London <hi>alſo ſave abundance of Money in their being forced to Run Threeſcore Miles after their Juſt Debts. But I have often admired at the Reaſon of putting His Majeſty to extraordinary needleſs Charge to carry away ſo many Hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Pounds from</hi> London <hi>to thoſe two miſerable Places</hi> Chatham <hi>and</hi> Portſmouth. <hi>and now I think of</hi> Chatham, Rocheſter, <hi>and</hi> Strood, <hi>makes me think of three Places Nick-named,</hi> Cheat them, Rot them, <hi>and</hi> Starve them; <hi>God grant that our Seamen and their Families be not any of them left to be Ruined there;</hi> but it is very ſtrange, that a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Town or two ſhould have more Friends to get the Ships paid off
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62670:21"/>laſt there, than the City of <hi>London</hi> ſhould to get them to be paid here? How Kiſſing goeth by Favour I know not; but now to have done with that, having almoſt tired my ſelf with Writing and yet leſt a great part unwritten that I ſhould, or might have written; will come to propoſe ſomething I promiſed for the Nations advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to ſome Millions of Money in a few Years, and it is this.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the <hi>Diſtilling Trade</hi> for <hi>Brandy</hi> do take up in one Year a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout One hundred Thouſand Quarters of Malt, and now ſuppoſe at 30 Shillings the Quarter, that is One hundred and fifty Thouſand Pound, which (by the way) is a prodigious Quantity of <hi>Corn,</hi> I was a going to ſay waſted, but I will ſay, Diſtilled out for Idle Tipple that our Forefathers heard not ſo much as the Name of; and it is no wonder Corn hath been ſo exceeding dear, and ſo many Poor ready to periſh, if there be near ſo much of it turn'd into Fire and Vapour, that it may be hath killed more Men and Women theſe late Years in <hi>England,</hi> than the Sword, and it fireth the very Souls of many out of their Bodies by degrees, if not preſently, as ſeveral have been, but by degrees I have known many, both Man and Women, have ſhorten'd their Lives many Years by drinking ſo much of ſuch fiery Drink, to dry up their very Livers or Lungs, and neither fear of Death, or any Wiſdom, Sence, or Reaſon can take off Mankind from what their Luſt and Appetites are ſet upon; and if there were an open Trade to <hi>France,</hi> if we ſhould but ſend a Million a Year of our Large Money for their Brandy and <hi>Wine,</hi> it would be the way to Begger us in a very few Years; therefore if we muſt have ſo much <hi>Brandy</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> I would humbly propoſe, That there might be a Law made to have our Hedge rows in every Field, by Act of Parliament, obliged in ſeven or eight Years time to have an Apple-Tree in every Thirty Foot of Hedges, and there might be ſeveral Millions of Apple-Trees planted in eight Years time, the Kernels of Appels now would the firſt two or three Years produce Nurſeries of Trees enough, and they in about ten or twelve years might come to bear Fruit; and being, as I ſaid, planted in the Hedg-rows. need not take up an Acre of Land for 40 Millions of Trees, and if the Trees comes to bear, would preſerve our Corn from being burnt up; I mean into Brandy, and it is our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Syder will make almoſt as good Brandy as the <hi>French;</hi> and if this Plantation were but Eſtabliſhed, it would Pay its own Charge of the Planting ten times over quickly,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62670:22"/>and if it was once taken up, it would never be laid down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; for Apples are for Meat and Drink to ſeveral poor Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in the Country, and at laſt the very wood of the <hi>Trees,</hi> if <hi>Forty Years Old,</hi> would be worth for Firing when they have done Bearing <hi>Fruit,</hi> five times the Charge of <hi>Planting,</hi> and as I ſaid, we need not loſe an Acre of Land, and if any would propoſe the Planting of Oaks after the ſame manner; one in every 30 Foot of Hedge-rows; Acorns are cheap enough, and if every twenty Foot had an Apple-tree and every twenty Foot an Oak, planted, the timber of one, and the Fruit of the other, would make the next age Rejoice, and have Cauſe to Bleſs. God for the Care of this, which makes me think of the Old Motto.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>He that delights to Plant and Set,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Makes after Ages in his Debt.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Now if after-Ages will be in debt to this for ſeveral new Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and Miſeries, and cheating Tricks, it is pitty; But they ſhould be in debt to us for ſeveral good Laws, and indeed good Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, and God grant they may be in debt to us, for ſome good good Reformation, that ſo Iniquity may not be our Ruin; and now having writ out all my Book, and made my Charge almoſt double what I deſigned by Printing ſo much in ſeveral Caſes more than I deſigned, and yet I could not well avoid it, being only guided by the good will and Pleaſure of God; but wanting a wiſer Head to let my Notions paſs through, and being always afraid to leave out my own honeſt Deſign to take in other Mens Wit, ſo that if I ſhould ſuffer for any part of it, I could with a good Conſcience bleſs God I have written every Word in the ſincerity of my Heart, in Love to <hi>God, and to His Majeſty, and the Parliament, and the Nation;</hi> for I am not of the Number of thoſe ſenſleſs Wretches, that would Fire the Houſe to deſtroy the Rats and Mice, neither long for Slavery, becauſe the King, and the Nation, and the Seamen have been ſo dreadfully Cheated ſince we had our Liberty; but I am of the honeſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Mind, who had ſome Brains in his Head when they told him, <hi>The Presbyterians were worſe than the Papiſts; No,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>That is falſe; For</hi> ſaid he, <hi>The Presbyterians would pull my Lawn Sleeves off, but the Papiſt would pull off my Skin.</hi> And this I would leave as a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62670:22"/>
               <hi>Memorandum</hi> for all thoſe who grumble againſt this Government, and would long for the Garlick and Onions of <hi>Egypt,</hi> I mean for a Popiſh King; that as the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters, and People did Plot and contrive to bring in King <hi>Chales</hi> II. and loſt ſome thouſands of their Lives for him before-hand, and yet when he came to the Crown, he would not Truſt one of them unto the day of his Death, but hated them, and ruined them, and their Religion, tho he was called a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and had been in <hi>Covenant with God, and that People,</hi> yet he broke through all Oaths that he took to them, and through all Bonds of Love or Gratitude; and how much more dreadfully would a Popiſh King Ruin all the Proteſtant Religion and People in <hi>England,</hi> if he were in Power? And now to have done, I Humbly beg Pardon of God, and of his Majeſty, King <hi>William,</hi> and of the Two moſt Honourable Houſes, for all that is amiſs in this or me, and that God would be the Protection of me and mine in and thro Chriſt, for time and all Eternity, and now to the <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, Three Perſons, and one Holy, Glorious, and only Wiſe God, be the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Praiſes,</hi> Amen. So prays he, who is His Moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Majeſty King <hi>William's</hi> Loyal, and Faithful Subject, and the Parliament, and Nations humble Servant, while</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> the 4th. 1698/9.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>William Hodges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>By reaſon of the Author's great diſtance from the Preſs, there is ſome ſmall <hi>Errata's;</hi> as Page 3. <hi>Lady-Day</hi> for <hi>May-day.</hi> And page 25. <hi>Propheſying</hi> inſtead of <hi>Profeſſing.</hi> The Reader is deſired to Correct them, or any other with his Pen. And the Author being not Born for himſelf, is willing to preſent every new Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Houſe of Commons with two Books: one about the Seamens Ruin, and the other Propoſals for their Incouragement. But not knowing which they are, will leave the Books with Mr. <hi>Applesby,</hi> their Door-keeper, for thoſe that pleaſe to call for them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
